<resources>
    <string name="app_name">The AGĨKŨYŨ</string>
    <string name="kihumo">
        The story of the Gikuyu begins at the tallest mountain in kenya, Kirinyaga(Mt. Kenya). This is believed to be the Holiest mountain in the world where Ngai lives. It is the only place where ira can be found, believed to be the soil of the place where Ngai used to walk when talking to Gikuyu. This very white soil, ira, symbolises how holy Ngai is. Gikuyu was created from the soil from Mukuyu tree gence the name Mugikuyu.He used to drink the milk from the Mukuyu.He was circumcised by Ngai on top of Kirinyaga and washed in the the 5 lakes found on top of the mountain.After he was healed he started to put the boundaries of the Gikuyu land. He started with Karimatura on the North,on the south was Kirimbiruiro (Ngong Hills).When he was coming from the south he could not go through the forest and Ngai created a way for him, the place is called Tuuthu. He found potatoes, beans and peas, he then went down the hill and found iria ria nyoni nyiingi(lake of many birds,lake nakuru),before reacjing the lake he passed by the rui rwa nyahururu (thompsons).\n
                He found raw peas and he was told by Ngai to eat and not to carry but he ate and carried.Mugikuyu ndariaga atatigitie. After eating the peas that he had carried, he experienced a very severe stomach ache and Ngai reminded him that he was not to carry the peas. Ngai gave him very tiny seeds to chew and they were very bitter. He was told to take the top soil from the floods. When he scooped the soil water came out.He called that lake karia ka mutaita/ngaita (lake Elementaita). The boundaries of Gikuyu land are: Karimatura,Kirinyanga,Kirimambogo/Kianjahi,karima ka munyu wa mburi,Nyandarua,kirima kiri ihoro,kirima kia nugu ikiruithia ihii ciacio,karima ka honge cia atumia,kirimbiruiro. The worship boundaries are Kirinyaga,Kirimbiruiro,kianjahi na Nyandarua.\n
                Gikuyu believed in Ngai, not out of fear of hell and its fire but because of knowing Ngai as He was.\n
                Ngai told Gikuyu to go and settle at Mukurwe wa Gathanga,he passed by Ndaraca ya Ngai which is there untill now.At Mukurwe wa Gathanga he met Mumbi(creator) and they could not touch each other because they were not used to each other.The first ceremony was that of Mumbi’s circumcision,she joined riika ria nemathi.Gikuyu was carrying muthigi,kimuri nad mondo and mumbi took these thing from him (kwaura) hence the reason of giving ngoima ya wauri during ruracio.(Muthuri atari mwaure ndakeruraga). Gikuyu offered a sacrifice asking Ngai to let him touch,undress and sleep with Mumbi,currently called ngoima ya njaga/gitithi in ruracio.\n
                Uthingu/guthinga=>Ni uhoti wa guikara utegwithahia,utekwiihia,utekwiananga hindi ciothe,handu hothe na mahinda mothe.\n
                Gikuyu and Mumbi were soo clean(athingu) thats why there is no known grave of either of them. Gikuyu left the homestead saying he was going to Kirinyanga to get ira for the children and pass by weru wa mukaaga to get munyu wa gatune. After few days Mumbi said she want to go and meet Gikuyu as he was coming from his journey and help him carry munyu wa gatune from weru wa mukaaga.\n

    </string>
    <string name="clans">
        \nBelow are the names of the daughters and their corresponding derivative clan names.
        The name starting with the prefix <i>Wa</i> is certainly the main name. Each may have more variants depending on location but the main names prefixed WA are conclusive.\n
\nMĩhĩrĩga ya Agĩkũyũ ,o Muhiriga niwari Mawega na mauru maruo ,no Kai Ruriri ni rwendaini muno\n
\nWanjirũ\n
\nWanjirũ nĩwe nyina wa mũhĩrĩga wa Anjirũ, na nĩ we warĩ irigithathi ria Gikũyũ. Nĩwe matũndura na no we wongire kĩnatha kĩa Mũmbi.Wanjirũ nĩwe waheire Mũmbi rĩtwa rĩake \‘Mũmbi\’. Nĩoĩ ũhoro wa mĩtĩ, arĩ ũrũme mũno,nĩ etaga nyamũ igoka na agacihoreria na nĩarĩ ũgĩ mũingĩ mũno.Nĩ mũtongoria na nĩahũthagĩra hinya ũtongoria-inĩ wake.Anjirũ nĩ mendete mahiũ na indo cia thakame na nĩ marĩ kĩĩo mũno. Mũthenya ũrĩa aciarirũo nogũo mũthenya ũrĩa Mũmbi ahotire kũmba nyũngũ na akĩmĩciina na ĩkĩira. Mũmbi endaga kũmwĩta Wanjirũ aririkanage ũirũ wa nyũngũ ĩrĩa ombĩte nake Gĩkũyũ endaga kũmwĩta Wamatu tondũ etĩkĩtĩe Ngai aikaraga matu-inĩ marĩa mairũ no nĩũndũ wa Mũmbi gũtindaga na mwana rĩtwa Wanjirũ nĩrĩo riarũmire. Anjirũ moĩ gũtuma inya kũrĩ mĩhĩrĩga yothe na nowe wĩna ũgĩ wa rũrigi rũngĩruta rũngi kĩnya. Mũnjirũ niari uugi wa urogi nanikio acukagwo atĩ e kaũndũ na kangĩ. Ũguo nĩ kũũga atĩ matigaga mbũthũ ya mĩthaiga ĩrĩa ĩ rũgoci thĩ.\n
\nNdari cia Anjirũ: ndĩwanguku(1), ndĩwangunĩia(2),nguna hĩbĩ(3), hĩbĩia(4) hĩrabae(5),wagacuma(6),cuma mande(7), manding\’ong\’o(8), kũrũgũyũ-ini(9), kũrũbi(10).\n
\nWambũi\n
\nWambũi nĩwe nyina wa Ambũi. Niwe wari itiema kana githũmba. Nĩwe warĩ mũthaka mũno harĩ airitu othe a Gĩkũyũ. Gũtirĩ cira ũremaga Mũmbũi na nĩ mũthikĩrĩria na no agũcokerere ũrĩa wothe wamwĩra. Mũmbũi nĩaririkanaga kaũndũ kahanĩkire tene ge kega kana ge koru. Ambũi matihũtanagia na ũrogi tondũ nĩ marĩ mũgiro watigirũo nĩ Wambũi matikanahutanie na mĩthaiga tondũ Wambũi nĩendete ciana mũno. Nĩwe wahandire mũgumo wa Thika akiũga e gũciara makinye haũ. Anjikũ na ambũi na aceera nĩmarĩ ndũgũ. Ambũi macukagwo atĩ matithiragwo nĩ mũkuru ũrĩ nda(ndariganagiruo),Nĩara mũno nĩamu hĩndĩ ya ng\’aragu meendirie kahĩĩ njahĩ. Yĩni makahumbĩte ta kairĩtu. Ambũi nĩ ciũmbani(kũgucĩrĩria adũ,ũmbani nĩ wa kĩruka)\n
\nNdari cia Ambui:undiũĩ(1), twĩrĩĩ(2),twanduta mugambo tumire cuka turima tucanjai kondoko kihuni/kondoko kariguni\n
\nWanjikũ\n
\nWanjikũ nĩwe nyina wa mũhĩrĩga wa Agacikũ. Nĩwe muruna wa Wambui. Oĩkaine na kĩĩo. Nĩmendete gukinyira kĩhoto muno na no aturie cira kĩharo na ndacenjagia urĩa auga. Nĩendete kuruta wĩra muno. Me wĩra-inĩ nĩho mĩhĩrĩga ĩno ĩngĩ yamenyeire gũthĩa, matiũĩ kũina. ũngĩenda mbegũ ya mũtĩ o wothe Agaciku nĩ moĩ,akoragũo na mbegũ icio ciothe ona cia mahiũ. Nĩ ciũmbani nĩ ũndũ wa ũtonga wao. Agaciku maticokagĩrĩra,anina ũndũ nĩariganĩrũo na ndagarũrũkaga. Nĩ maigũithanĩtie na mĩhĩrĩga yothe. Ahana mwaki wa njikũ wa kĩganda kĩa igera. Agacikũ macukagwo nĩ ndogothi tondũ matiũĩ ithĩya. No me Ngumo nene nĩundũ wa kĩo kĩao.\n
\nNdari cia Agaciku: ũndĩu(1), tanda(2), mamba(3), kabũkũ(4), kandi(5), thimba(6), gĩtĩ(7), taratara(8), kamũcũrĩ(9), ciikũ(10).\n
\nWaceera kana Wanjeeri\n
\nWaceera kana Njeeri nĩwe nyina wa mũhĩrĩga wa Aceera. Nĩ etagwo na rĩtwa rĩngĩ rĩa kũnanio Wanjeri. Nĩo marĩ athigani,nĩ mũtuĩria wa maũndũ, etĩkĩtie ũndũ wothe wagagĩrĩra wona awĩka,nĩoĩ thũgũrĩ,nĩ marĩ hitho na matiĩhokanaga o ene. Mũcera ndagũthũkaga kana kũrakaria mũndũ o ũgũo. Uhoro wothe nĩo moragio kana nĩmaũiguĩte. Atũmũo kĩama nĩakinyagia ũhoro,nĩmarĩ ciũria njega nĩgetha anyite ũndũ ũrĩa arenda, ũgĩ wake aũrutagia kuuma kamũrita, mũri wa itumu, mũri wa hinya,mũri wa ĩrio,mũri wa maĩ,mũri wa ũgitĩri,mũri wa mathaga na mũri wa ũciari.Ungĩrakaria mucera ndagakũohera. Mũhĩrĩga ũyũ ũĩkaine nĩ ũndũ wa waara wao wa mũcarĩrie na uramati wa indo, amu mũcera acukagwo atĩ ndaceraga na ũngĩ.\n
\nNdari cia Anjeri: nĩ mbuũkũ(1), na ngara(2), ciacemania(3), ikũbĩ-inĩ(4), rĩa mũthoni(5),cioina rũtĩ(6),rũtĩndĩ(7),mbũri ikũmi(8), cia acera(9), igakũmĩra(10)\n
\nWaithĩra kana Wangeci\n
\nWangeci kana Waithĩra nĩwe mũciari wa mũhĩrĩga wa Aithĩrandũ kana Angeci na ari mũruna wa Njeeri. Ngeci nĩ ũrũme na waithera riumanĩte na ũtheru,ekaga maũndũ make magaithĩrana. Moĩkane na ũrũme wa mbara,ũngĩkora makĩrũa o ene ndũkaingĩrĩre. Nĩo matongoragia ngarawani ya rũrĩrĩ,(ngerewani ndĩtũngagũo), mbara ciothe cia Gĩkũyũ ciatongoragio nĩ Angeci. Mũngeci nĩ mũtana mũno,kĩrĩa atangĩkũhe no kĩrĩa atarĩ na aheanaga na ngoro yothe. Matigaga maũndũ ngoro. Nĩ arĩmi, arĩithi , ciũmbani, nĩmarũtaga makarau na nĩmarĩ ũgo wao. Nĩ maiguithanĩtie na mĩhĩrĩga yothe nĩ tondũ wa ũcamba wake. Aya nĩo a mũhĩrĩga utari ũcuke, no rũgiti na mbaara na haaro ciao itirirĩkaga, na ndangĩkuonia ciande. Arũme ao nĩo matongoragia ita.\n
\nNdari cia Aithĩrandũ: teerĩ(1),tandaya(2),cuubi(3), cubicu(4), ikuna(5), kaiiba(6), bebere(7), beburu(8), gĩkũna(9), ng\’o(10)\n
\nWangarĩ kana mũithekahuno\n
\nWangarĩ nĩwe Nyina wa Angarĩ na noo Aithekahuno. Aciarĩtũo atigĩtie thikũ na o nake arigithathire ciana itakinyĩtie thikũ. Arindirũo nyũngũ-inĩ na ndumbũ ĩgĩtuĩka \‘incubator\’ na rĩrĩa kaũmire karĩ na mara ma ndumbũ gakĩoneka kahana ngarĩ na gagĩtuo Wangarĩ, arigithathire tũhĩĩ tũĩri twarĩ tũhuno na agĩtuo mũithekahuno. Nĩ atheru ta ndumbũ , nĩ ciũmbani, nĩmarĩ kĩnyũrũri, nĩendete mbara (mbara yake ndĩigagũo), nĩarĩmi, na nĩmarĩ ũkarĩ na no marĩ kaũiru. Wũiru nĩ kĩĩo Nĩ makuhanĩrĩirie na Waithera.Nĩ macukagwo na makahũhio nĩ mĩhĩrĩga ĩria ĩngĩ atĩ nĩ maatĩririe wĩra ndũma cia wĩra ciahĩa na ciatũka. Matĩririe wĩra mambe marĩe ndũma marĩoiki na ũcio nĩ ũkarĩ.\n
\nNyambura kana Akĩũrũ kana Ethaga\n
\nNyambura nĩwe nyina wa Ethaga. Ethaga ni mũhĩrĩga mwĩtigĩre mũno Niamu nĩo maagitagĩra rũrĩrĩ rũtigatwĩke rwaganu. Uguo mekaga na kũroga na mĩario ya kanua andũ aganu magaikara metigĩrĩte.. No marĩ aturi na no mahuhaga mbura ‘Macukagwo ati “Mwithaga atongaga ũtukũ”. Nĩamu wĩra ũcio wakũhahũra eki naĩ warĩhagwo ũtukũ andũ matekũmenya.\n
\nWairimũ kana Gathiigia\n
\nWairimũ nĩwe nyina wa mũhĩrĩga wa Airimũ kana Agathigia. Acio nao nĩa mũhĩrĩga wa mwanya mũno, amu macukagwo ati Mũirimũ kana Mũgathiigia agũire na mũtĩ ni ũndũ wa kwenda aka. Yĩni kwĩgũithia na mũtĩ nĩguo mũirĩtu amũigwĩre tha amũhikĩre.\n
\nWangũi- Kana Waithiegeni\n
\nWangũi nĩwe nyina wa mũhĩrĩga wa Angũi kana Aithiegeni, Aithiageni macukagwo nĩ ũiru na rũitho na nokĩo metagwo mbarĩ ya mũtinia ngingo. No ningĩ nĩ akũi a nyĩmbo moma na ciumbani\n
\nWamũyũ kana Warigia\n
\nWamũyũ nĩwe warĩ kahinga nda ga Gĩkũyũ na Mũmbi na nĩwe nyina wa Aicakamũyũ. Warigia nĩ acukagwo atĩ nĩomirie mĩgiyo Ndia. Nĩguo mũhĩrĩga ũrĩa ũrĩ ũtana mũno. Nĩwe wagire mũrũme na angĩagire gũtanaha ndangĩagĩire ciana\n
\nWhen the girls became of age and began to have yearnings for their own husbands, they went to their mother and asked her where she got her\’s. She took the problem to her husband <i>Gikuyu. Gikuyu</i> consulted <i>Ngai</i>, God and <i>Ngai</i> asked him to make a sacrifice of a spotless ram under the fig tree <i>“Mugumo”</i>.
        He called his daughters and asked them to go to the <i>Mukuyu</i> and for them to cut for each a straight rod of her own height. Nine of the girls brought the rods
        and their father placed them on top of the fire as <i>ndara</i> and then placed the sacrifice on them. In the morning NINE young men appeared and each of the daughters took a mate her own height.
        Apparently, there is confusion in the myths as to whether nine, relating to the young men means nine in the real sense or it meant “nine full”.
        What seems to emerge from the various stories is that one of the daughters, Wamuyu was too young to take part in the rods\’ business and their heating (ahem! Let me swallow that one) but nevertheless later had children and descendants.
    </string>
    <string name="ngeithi">
        \nGreetings in <i>Gīkūyū</i> can be complicated. In order to understand <i>Gīkūyū</i> traditional greetings it is necessary to first define some terms.\n
\n<i><b>Maitū</b></i> means Mother and not just the biological mother but all women who are the approximate age of your mother. She will greet all young men <i>Wakīa Awa</i> and young women as <i>Wakīa Iiyū</i> and they will reply, <i>Wakīa Maitū</i> – Hail! my mother!\n
\n<i><b>Awa</b></i> means Father and all men of the approximate age of your father. He will greet all young women <i>Wakīa Maitū</i> and young men <i>Wanyua Awa</i> and the girl will reply <i>Wakīa Awa</i> while the boy will reply, <i>Wanyua Awa</i> – Hail! my father!\n
\n<i><b>Cūcū</b></i> means Grandmother and all women of the approximate age of your Granny will greet you <i>Wakīa Cūcū</i>. The reply is the same.\n
\n<i><b>Wakinī</b></i> means male agemate so they will greet each other <i>Wakīa Wakinī</i> and with the same reply.\n
\n<i><b>Wanyua</b></i> means male drinking buddies. They will greet each other <i>Wakīa Wanyua</i> or simply <i>Wanyua</i>! with the same reply. Young men before their first born daughter or son is circumcised did not qualify to drink beer and thus were <i>Wakinī.</i>\n
\n<i><b>Thiritū</b></i> is girl friendship so you will hear girls addressing each other as <i>Wathurutia!</i> Young girls’ hand greetings are complex and full of hidden messages and meanings impossible to decode unless one is in their loop.\n
\nBoys address each other as <i><b>Mūriū!</b></i> – Son of my Mother and address young girl peers as <i><b>Wamwarī</b></i>, Daughter of my Mother and many other group variations like those of girls.\n
\n<i><b>Ūrata</b></i> is a is a loving relationship of opposite sexes so you will hear a man addressing an age-mate or age-mate’s wife as <i>Wakīa Mūrata</i> and she replying the same. Remember man-man is <i>Wakinī or Wanyua</i> and girl-girl is <i>Thurutia</i> so don’t as a man make the mistake of addressing your man friend, <i>Wakīa Mūrata</i>. Joker.\n
\n<i>Ūiru</i> means jealousy and because co-wives are jealous of each other they greet each other <i>Wakīa Kairu</i>. The reply is the same. Because many women today share husbands without knowing it, they should greet each other, <i>Wakīa Kairu!</i> – Hail! My Jealousy!\n
\nThe women mother-in-laws are <i>Wakīa Kanyanya</i> to one another – My little tomato.\n
\nThe women of her approximate age who welcome a newly-wed into a village are flowers to each other thus <i>Wakīa Mahūa</i> – My flowers.\n
\nThe general rule is that the older person usually initiates the greeting and between male and female the male initiates the greeting. It is not proper for a girl to look at an older man in the eye but will look aside or below making patterns with her toe. Young men do not also meet their mother’s gaze but will look away as they answer. Women raise their hands and tap each other’s palms while girls do all sorts of cheeky tricks with their fingers and arms. Men grip each other’s right arm firmly and not hand greeting. Men who were initiated together always have a special bond as blood brothers who share anything even wives since they shared the knife. During initiation they developed a secret greeting so that even if one were to travel far and meet an age-mate, they would recognize each other from the greeting, much like Freemasons. One would host the other warmly in his homestead and even offer him one of his wives for the night. Men and women did not share hand greetings.\n
\nThe <i>Gīkūyū</i> system of naming children is simple. The first born son is named after his paternal grandfather. The second son is named after the maternal grandfather. The third son is named after his oldest paternal uncle. The forth son is named after the oldest maternal uncle and so forth. The girls are named using the same system. There can be no skipping of anybody for reasons of not liking that person or any other reason. Twins are both named on the same side and never named on both the paternal and maternal sides but on the side the first twin happens to fall.\n
\nThis discussion of the naming system is important as the person partakes of the Spirit of the one he or she is named after. If the child is named after a departed Soul, he or she is considered the reincarnation of the departed relation. Because of this naming system it is normal to hear an old woman greeting a very young man, seeing in him her husband, as <i>“ūūūūi! Wakīa Mūrata! Ūyū nī Mūthuuri ūrīa wakwa?” – Ohhh! </i> This is my lover! The young man must reply, often in embarrassment,  <i>“Wakīa Mūrata!” </i> – Hail! my lover! It is old women who had the habit of greeting young men thus. Men did not usually do this to little girls.\n
\nIt is important that we note that a man greeted his daughter and all girls below his age as <i>Wakīa Maitū</i>  – Hail my Mother! This would mean that every little girl, even to an old man, <i>Guuka</i> , is necessarily his mother, though she will reply, <i>Wakīa Guuka</i>  – Hail! my grandfather! When a man met an older or younger woman on the road he saw in her his mother or his daughter. Since his daughter is his reincarnated mother, the greeting is always, <i>Wakīa Maitū</i>  – Hail! my Mother! It would then have been impossible to cross boundaries as is happening today when young girls greet older men, Hi Daddy! and he replies, Hi Sweetie! This piece of traditional etiquette and morality is lost when we fail to comprehend this naming system. For a man, his second daughter is always his wife’s mother. All in-laws in <i>Gīkūyū</i> are people who are handled with velvet gloves. One is meant to be a little shy in their presence, (Because cough, cough). Because of this strong boundary between a man and his mother in law, he cannot bring himself to shout her name in his house and therefore calls his second daughter, <i>Mūthoni </i> – My Shy, regardless of whether the mother-in-law’s name was <i>Wangeci or Wambui</i> . It is not in order for him to shout, Wangeci!\n
\nWe advice young men to reply  <i>Wakīa Maitū</i> to women who greet them  <i>Nīatia!</i> (literally, What is it!?) What is it she is asking when she asks,  <i>Ūrī mwega?</i> – How good are you? Good for what? Likewise, young women should reply to advances of “Hi Baby!” with  <i>Wakīa Awa!</i> – Hail! my father! Traditionally,  <i>Ūrī Mūhoro, Ūrī Mwega, Kūhana Atīa</i>, asking on the health etc. of the other party came as secondary greetings after the formal address of  <i>Wakīa</i>, Hail, NEVER before as is normal today.\n
\nIt is high time we returned human relationships to their proper sense of etiquette otherwise this is the reason why men are ending up having carnal relations with young girls, their mothers. The <i>Gīkūyū</i> say, <i>Kīrīra nī ūūra thoni</i>, that is, in order to impart true wisdom, <i>Kīrīra</i>, it is necessary to be explicit – or not too near your in-law. It is our hope that this post will help this generation to rediscover the riches hidden in their traditional practices like greetings and naming systems which they consider outdated or archaic.\n
\nThis is an urgent call for the re-estamblishment of the social boundaries that have been uprooted by the corrupting influence of mindless Westernization. One way to start is to make sure the formal greetings are learnt by all and used at all times.\n
    </string>
    <string name="migiro">
        The moral ethic and code of behavior of the <i>Gīkūyū</i> was however not governed by fear of a God or the action of spirits but largely by a system of taboo. There was a long list of dos’ and don’ts called <i>thahu</i> or abominables and lesser <i>mugiro</i> or prohibitions. There was a prescribed cause of action for undoing the expected ill-effects of breaking any one of the taboos. Many of them required a certain purification procedure sometimes by a medicine-man depending on the severity of the taboo broken and usually involved the sacrifice of a goat. Because of the heavy cost both emotional and economic of breaking taboos, behavior was thus controlled. When the cost of sinning was later devalued by the white <i>Mundu Mugo, Mubia</i>, to payment after death in a mystical so-called hell, the <i>Gīkūyū</i> Pandora’s Box was opened.\n
\nThese taboos for all manner of things may seem to us today as dealing with trivial matters but each prohibition was grounded in sound reasoning with the people’s protection in mind. For instance it was <i>thahu</i> for a child to fall off its mothers back and the punishment required purification ceremonies to the mother and child. It is obvious that such an ‘abominable thing’, or <i>thahu</i> was similar to the stringent specifications that are set out for the manufacture and sale of baby carriages today. Another <i>thahu</i> was, ‘it is <i>thahu</i>, for a lizard to fall into the fireplace in a hut’. The remedy for this <i>thahu</i> was for the entire hut to be demolished and a new one built. It looks like it was a drastic step to take to remedy a small matter but when considered more closely it turns out to have been anchored in sound reasoning. The fact that a lizard had found its way into the grass thatch was evidence that there were so many insects in the grass as to attract the lizards, so the argument went; and if there were insects, it meant that the smoke was not curing the grass enough to keep away insects and thus the grass must be rotting. Such a roof could not be trusted and had to be demolished at once before it fell on the occupants resulting in a greater tragedy. There were many taboos like these associated with the house and the homestead but many of them are not documented and are still in oral tradition form.\n
\nBreaking a prohibition, <i>mugiro</i> results in an unclean state of abomination, <i>thahu</i> which is removed through chastisement and sometimes involves a vomiting out ritual by the offender, <i>gutahikio</i>. This vomiting out ritual returns the offender back into the pure state of being.\n
\nBecause a person dying inside the hut rendered it unclean, and the hut had to be burned down, when a person was believed to be close to death he was taken out and built a small shelter in the bush where he could be cared for till he died. Sometimes a person recovered and came back after the healing though he had to go through purification before acceptance back into the village or homestead. If he died inside the hut, his body had to be removed before the hut was burned down and since it was taboo to handle a dead body, a hole was broken in the back wall of the hut so that hyenas can enter and remove the body. Alternatively, a person who was untouchable by the <i>thahu</i> of a dead body was found and paid to remove the body.
\nA list of all the taboos and prohibitions is a tall order to compile but a sampling of the rules and regulations governing just the homestead and the house from Leakey and others is hereby given to illustrate the importance of the taboo system in the day-to-day maintenance of a <i>Gīkūyū</i> homestead. There were several levels of severity of the prohibitions and while some were merely bad form, others required purifications by a <i>Mundu Mugo</i>. These were equivalent to modern building By-laws.\n
    </string>
    <string name="migiro_label">Migiro</string>
    <string name="kihumo_label">Kihumo</string>
    <string name="calendar_label">Calendar</string>
    <string name="clans_label">Mihiriga</string>
    <string name="ngeithi_label">Ngeithi Cia Ugikuyu</string>
    <string name="stages_label">Life Stages</string>
    <string name="secondbirth_label">Gucokia Mwana Ihu-ini</string>
    <string name="nyumba_label">Mucii wa Gikuyu</string>
    <string name="ngwiko_label">Sex Education</string>
    <string name="uhikania_label">Uhikania</string>
    <string name="names_label">Family Nmaes</string>
    <string name="thimo_label">Thimo Cia GĨKŨYŨ</string>
    <string name="urathi_wa_mugo">Mugo Wa Kibiru</string>


    <string name="thimo">
        \nAgĩkũyũ moĩ kũhitha ndĩa, matiũĩ kũhitha ũhoro.\n
Ageni erĩ matirĩ ũtugĩre\n
Aka eeri nĩ nyũngũ igĩrĩ cia ũrogi\n
Andũ maiganaine magĩthiĩ na magĩceera\n

\nCia mũkarĩ irĩagwo na mambura\n
Ciakorire Wacũ mũgũnda\n
Ciethanaga ikiũmba, ikiũmbũka itirĩ ndũgũ\n
Cira mũingĩ nĩ wa ũthoni ũgĩkua\n
Ciira ũtũragia ũkĩa mũciĩ\n
Cia nyiha iguraga ndikuria\n
Ciunagwo rũkomo kĩmenyi akamenya\n

\nGĩcegũ kĩa andũ aingĩ ti kĩega\n
Gũtirĩ ũũi ta Ngai\n
Gũtirĩ mũnini mũkia\n
Gũtirĩ ĩrumaga imera igĩri\n
Gũtirĩ yuraga na ndĩkĩe\n
Gĩikaro kĩmwe kĩ ndaa\n
Gatuma koragithirie watatua\n
Gũtirĩ mũrĩo ũtainia rũthĩa\n
Gakwĩrũmĩra gatioragia mũgũgũta\n
Gatitũ karĩ ngoro gatiunanagĩrwo.\n
Gũtirĩ wĩ kahĩĩ ũtakaharwo mũtwe\n
Gũtũ gwakahũka gũticoka ndebe\n
Gũtirĩ ngoma ĩtarĩ mũmĩenji\n
Gũciara ũru ti kwenda kwa mwene\n
Gũtirĩ wanda na wamũgongo.\n
Gũtirĩ kũraya kwĩ njahĩ hũũre.\n
Gũtirĩ ngũrani ya hiti na wamũtĩrĩ\n
Gũtirĩ mũciĩ ũtarĩ mũringiti wa thĩna\n
Gĩtiiro kĩa mũka wene gĩtikagio abuĩria\n
Gatitu ka mũimwo nĩ irĩ noko karĩ mĩtĩ\n
Gategwa kanini kahaicaga na mbere\n
Gũtirĩ mũndũ wendaga gũtũngana na nyoni njũru\n

\nHinga itikinyaga iraka\n
Hiti ĩkĩnyiria ndĩnoraga\n
Harĩ athuri hatitangagwo maaĩ.\n

\nĨganagwo yarĩ iria yakua\n
Ihĩĩ itithiaga ũthoni\n
Itihingagia mbugi.\n
Irĩ gĩkũyũ itirĩ ũkabi\n
Itonga igĩri itirĩ nyoni.\n
Ĩganagwo yarĩ iria yakua\n
Ĩthe wa athaka ndarĩ matũ\n
Itherũ rĩtirutagĩrwo mũgwĩ.\n
Ĩreragĩra rũkũ-inĩ ĩkaya kũigana\n
Irĩaga na mbugi ona kũri ũgũati\n
Ĩtarĩ hinya ĩnyuaga munju.\n
Ĩtoĩ ĩngĩ ĩmĩnungagĩra na thutha\n
Ĩngĩhĩtia na mũgwĩ ndĩrathaga na njoya\n
Ĩta rĩtarĩ ndundu rĩhũragwo na njũgũma ĩmwe\n

\nKaihũ gacangacangi gatigaga kwao gũgĩthĩnjwo\n
Kanya gatune nĩ mwamũkanĩro\n
Karĩ guoya kainũkĩire nyina ge kagima\n
Kahiga gakũrũ gatiagararagwo nĩ maĩ\n
Kagũrũ ke ime gakĩrĩte ke mũhu.\n
Karonda ka mwene gatimũiragia ngoro\n
Kĩndũ kĩnene kĩũru no kĩronda\n
Kĩndũ no mwene mũhoi ahoe\n
Kũhoha ti kũũma\n
Kwĩgaya ti gũkua\n
Kĩrĩra nĩ ũra thoni\n
Kũganwo nĩ kũũra\n
Kũrĩ gũkua mũrio ta kĩgwa.\n
Kiumaga mbũri kĩeremia\n
Kĩnya kĩrĩ itina nĩkĩo kĩigaga\n
Kĩonje kĩrumaga mukĩhiũhĩria\n
Kĩamĩa kĩmwe ciamĩa ciothe\n
Kanua kendagia ngingo\n
Komũ athĩnirie kaigũ wanyina\n
Kĩrimũ kĩega no kĩa iria\n
Kũmenya werũ nĩ kũũtinda\n
Kwa mwendwa gũtirĩ irĩma\n
Kwĩrĩrwo ti kũneo\n
Kĩnya gĩtihatagĩrĩrio rũga\n
Kĩnyuĩro tikio gĩtothinĩro\n
Kĩrimũ kĩhaicaga mũtĩ na iratũ.\n
Kĩndũ kĩene kĩnoragia itina rĩmwe\n
Kĩrimũ kĩahũna kiugaga nĩkĩanora\n
Kamamĩrĩria kaharũrũkagia mwatũ\n
Kĩrimũ nĩ kĩũru kĩongaga nyina akuĩte\n
Kĩambĩrĩria kĩa ũũgĩ nĩ gwĩtigĩra Ngai\n
Kĩgwa gĩakũra gĩcokagia mũrĩo gĩtina.\n
Kĩũmbani kĩaga gũkua kĩonaga nganga mbute\n
Kwa mwaria gukĩũra kwa mũkiri kworire tene\n
Kũrũga ti kwega tondũ kĩũra kĩoragire ũthoni na irũga.\n

\nMaguta makũrũ matiinaga rwĩmbo\n
Mumagari ndaumbĩkaga irigu\n
Mũcera na mũkũndũ akũndũkaga take\n
Mũhiki mũthaka ahĩtũkagĩra thome wa ngĩa\n
Mĩcii ni ndogo \n
Mũciĩ ũkuagwo ngagũro\n
Mũthiĩrwo ũgo no ũrĩa akerwo.\n
Mĩciĩ yũraga ng\'o ciaigĩrĩrwo makumbĩ-inĩ\n
Mũciĩ wĩ inooro ndũtuhagia kahiũ\n
Mũici na mũndũ mũka akenaga akua\n
Muici na kihii akenaga kiarua\n
Mũremwo nĩ ndũgo egwatagia njaa ĩĩ mahiga\n
Mũremwo nĩ nguĩko egwatagia huuyo\n
Mũrega akĩrwo ndaregaga akĩhetwo\n
Mũikari mũtĩ gĩtina nĩwe ũũgĩ thambo iriaga kĩ\n
Mũũgĩ nĩ mũtaare\n
Mwĩĩri eĩtaga nyoko\n
Mũrĩmi ndaunagwo moko\n
Mumi na nja arĩaga mara\n
Mwendi ũthaka ndacayaga\n
Mũgeni amĩaga mbĩrĩra\n
Mũgũnda ũũraga na rũteere.\n
Mũtino ũthatagia ndigĩrĩri.\n
Mbura ĩtekura ĩgwatagia rũhuho\n
Mũkũrĩra gĩthũnũ ndoonagwo.\n
Mũgũnda mũkũrũ ndwagaga ũmatho\n
Mũguĩ wa ũtukũ ũcokagĩra harĩa wokĩra\n
Mũka mũkũrũ acokagĩrĩrwo na maithori\n
Mũndũ mũũgi ndarĩ mĩhere ya ũhoro\n
Mũndũ athugumaga na gatirũ gake\n
Mbembe nĩ mũthandũrano o ũrĩa ũkarigia na mũcakwe\n
Mũndũ wĩna rwake atihagio nĩ mwengũ wa mũka\n
Mũndũrũme ũtarĩ mbũri ndaragia ciaka\n
Mũrigia nakĩo nĩwe ũgĩkagĩra nguo\n
Mũcharia ũngĩ ndamũagaga.\n
Mũka mwerũ nĩ magambo\n
Mũheria ngĩa ndagiragia gũkĩe\n
Mũrega akĩrwo ndaregaga akĩhetwo\n
Mũtũri mũno ndaagaga\n
Mũndũ wa nda no ta wa kĩrumi. \n
Mbũri ngũrũ ndĩtiihaga tũhũ.\n
Mũhehwo na matũ meerĩ ndaiguaga.\n
Mũkũrũ gaya ũnyonie kũgaya\n
Mũmĩethi na ũmĩrĩte ndangĩmĩona.\n
Mũharwo nĩwe ũthingataga gĩthaka\n
Mũceera na mũkũndũ akũndũkaga o take\n
Mũciairĩ wa hiti akamagwo na ihĩndĩ\n
Mũkũrũ nĩatũmagwo no kũrumwo atarumagwo\n
Mũikarania na kĩimba ndaagaga maithori\n
Mũhiitha njaga ndaciaraga\n
Mũkungi aakorire mũcemi\n
Mwĩhĩti na mwana nĩ ũtamũrĩ\n
Mwĩtemengeri ndooragia ikĩhooha.\n
Mũgumo wakũrũka nĩ ithare rĩmeraga\n
Mbũri ndiunĩkaga ĩrĩa thondu\n
Mũikia ndooi mwehereri\n
Mũceera na mumo nĩ mwĩtĩkĩri\n
Mwana wĩ kĩyo ndaagaga mũthambia\n
Mbogo nyingĩ itirĩ thaathi\n
Moko maingĩ mamenanagĩra makĩrĩa\n
Mwaka wa hiti ndũhoyanagwo riigĩ\n
Mwendi kagwaci gatungu nĩ kwenjera\n
Mwĩhĩta na mwana nĩ atamurĩ\n
Mũrũmĩrwo ndamenyaga igĩthira\n
Maitho ma arũme ti mairang\'a\n
Mwaki wa Ngai ũraragio nĩ igoto\n
Mũtĩ ũtegũtemwo ndũgerekagwo ithanwa\n
Mũthakwa wathĩ ndũthiragwo nĩ gĩcanjara\n
Mũkomania mwaki ũtarĩ thenya ndaninaga ndogo\n
Mũrĩo nĩwĩrĩyagĩra, nĩũninaga magego, na ndũninaga ng\'aragu\n
Mburungo nini irĩ mũthiomeri ĩkĩrĩte mburungo nene ĩtarĩ mũthiomeri.\n

\nNdore ĩimbagio nĩ gĩtĩ\n
Ndindĩko ĩrĩ magũrũ\n
Ndia ndiku ĩikagio mũti\n
Njigua ĩrĩ matũ\n
Nĩyũmbũkaga ĩmbute\n
Nyeki ya nja ndĩrĩkaga.\n
Njahĩ nĩĩrĩ mũkimĩre\n
Nyũmba na riika itiumanagwo\n
Njũgũma njega yumaga ikũrĩro\n
Nyoni ngĩgu yakaga irigũ-inĩ ikũrũ\n
Ngarĩ ĩhĩtagwo nĩ mũndũ na mũthoniwe \n
Njĩra ya mũũri ĩgĩaga ime rĩ mũgaa\n
Ngatia yaaga nyama ĩrĩaga nyeki\n
Nguĩko ya mũndũrũme nĩ nda\n
Njukũ ni migathĩ ya itonga.\n
Ndia ngiri yaniina andũ.\n
Njamba nini ndĩnyakagwo\n
Nguyo ĩimbagio nĩ mahũbĩ\n
Njũkiĩ ndĩambaga na igua\n
Ngware ndĩũragagĩrwo nja.\n
Ndururumo igĩri itiiguanaga.\n
Ndũgũ nyingĩ ithatagia mũhuko.\n
Njamba ĩmwe ndĩhingagĩrĩria iriũko\n
Njĩra ya mũndũ ũmwe ĩthiagĩrwo gũtuka\n
Nyũmba ĩmenyagwo nĩ mũrari ti mũroki\n
Ngingo ya mũria ng\'ũũrũ nĩ gĩthitũ na rũrigi.\n
Ndĩakagwo ta ya wakinĩ no nĩ iyagwo mũrathĩre\n
Ng\'ombe ĩtarĩ mũting\'oe ĩhuragũo ngi nĩ Ngai\n
Ngwacĩ ya mwana wene noyo ĩhoragia mwaki\n
Nyongi nĩ ĩgimaraga ĩkarũmũkia rũnyondo\n

\nRũtwaraga nginya mũthambĩri\n
Rwĩ itara rũthekaga rwĩ riko.\n
Rũrĩra rũtithambagio rũũi.\n
Rwa gwĩcũtha rũtirĩĩ ruo.\n
Rũrigi rũri nja rũtiagaga gĩa kwoha \n
Rũruka rwa kĩmbu rũtithiragwo nĩ mũng\'ũng\'ũtũ\n

\nThũngũri ti ĩmwe ĩ marigũ\n
Thiaka ũiniĩ ndwagaga gũita mĩgwĩ.\n
Thia ndĩthũire mũmĩoni ta mũmĩanĩrĩri\n
Thegere igĩrĩ itiremagwo nĩ mwatũ\n
Thundo ya kahĩĩ ti ya mũrigono\n

\nŨtarĩ nĩ mũigĩre\n
Ũtamerithĩtie ndatigaga kũhanda\n
Ũtaana mũũru no wa kĩrĩgũ. \n
Ũtakanyuĩrĩire ndoĩ karĩ rita.\n
Ũtenderũ ũrĩ nja ndũrĩ mĩĩthemere\n
Ũthuri wa itonga ndũnungaga\n

\nWainaga nieroragĩra\n
Warũgaga nĩatobokaga\n
Wainaga nieroragira\n
Wendo nĩ ũtumumu\n
Wĩra ũrutagwo mwĩruti.\n
Wanyima thuni ngakũima mbogo\n
Wamũcoka nĩguo ũrĩaga mũndũ\n
Waica kehiri nowe waica keruti\n
Wakahare akuire agĩetha ngumo\n
Wathatire akĩrĩra waciarire no ararĩra\n
Wanarũmwo nĩ nyoka onaga kamũkwa akora\n
Weka wega nĩwe weĩka na weka ũũru nowe weĩka\n

\nYaikio ĩikagia ĩngĩ\n
Ya matharara ĩgwatagia ya nyeki\n
Yenda mũno ĩkũũraga rũrĩra\n
Ya riika rĩngĩ ĩrĩaga ĩkĩhurunjaga.\n
Yerwo nĩ noru ndĩnerwo ĩthĩnjwo\n
    </string>
    <string name="migiro_details">Details</string>
    <string name="migiro_example">Examples</string>
    <string name="thahu_migiro">
\n1. It was forbidden for a hut to have two doors.\n
\n2. It was taboo to lean a spear up against the roof of a hut. All spears had to be either stuck in the ground, or leaned against the fence or under the eaves. There was no penalty for breaking this taboo, but it was never done. Under no circumstance is a spear allowed inside the hut of a woman.\n
\n3. The door is a sliding one and is not hinged and it must always be opened on the side that a man’s father and grandfather opened it. If a person opens it on the wrong side he must go out again, shut the door, and re-enter correctly: otherwise he may not eat any food in the hut.\n
\n4. No one may close the door other than the owner of the hut. A visitor may open the door to enter, but closing the door must be left to the woman or her sons.\n
\n5. A husband may not shut the door of his hut save on his wedding night.\n
\n6. When entering a hut, a person had to pass and enter the kitchen space on the side of the fattening ram’s pen, gicegu.\n
\n7. You may not keep standing inside a hut. If you do not want to sit then you must go and stand outside.\n
\n8. It is taboo for young boys and girls to swing with the door lintel. They are wishing the death of their parents.\n
\n9. It was taboo for a man to sleep on the side by the outer wall of his wife’s bed.\n
\n10. It was taboo to start moving a woman’s hut to a new site while she was menstruating.\n
\n11. It was taboo for a fire in a hut to go out at any time when beer was being brewed in that hut, or when any special ceremony or sacrifice was taking place in that hut or in connection with it.\n
\n12. In no circumstances might all the fires in a homestead be allowed to go out together. For the purposes of this rule the subsidiary homestead of a married son attached to his father’s homestead counted as part of the main homestead.\n
\n13. If a cooking pot cracked while food was being cooked in it, that food might not be eaten except by women past childbearing.\n
\n14. If a woman was preparing castor oil from castor oil berries, and during the process of heating them over the fire, she either let them boil over or dry up in the pot, a purification ceremony and sacrifice was essential.\n
\n15. Should anyone in anger or drunkenness pluck thatch from any hut in a homestead, a sacrifice and purification would be essential to avoid disaster.\n
\n16. In a woman’s Nyumba, the head end of her bed was towards the thegi and the foot end towards the The head end of the girls’ bed was towards the gicegu and the fool; end towards the thegi (see Fig. 3.13). It was taboo for anyone to sleep in these beds except with their head at the head end of the bed.\n
\n17. A circumcised man may not under any circumstance approach the side of his mother’s side of the kitchen or touch her bed.\n
\n18. Young unmarried girls who are circumcised may not sit on the Kweru side of the kitchen but must sit on their bed side. All grown men had to sit on the Ruri side of the hut.\n
\n19. There is only one fireplace in a hut consisting of three stones. In the event of a temporary secondary fireplace being created by the addition of a two more stones, the head of the family may not eat food from that secondary fireplace.\n
\n20. If the fire drying rack above the fireplace, (itara) breaks and falls, a sacrifice must be done to replace it.\n
\n21. It was prohibited to pass food through a crack in the wall of a hut. Such food had to be taken out and brought in through the door before it could be eaten.\n
\n22. It is not permitted to pass food over the fireplace to a person on the other side, nor can food be taken around a pole. Food passed over the door may not be eaten by the head of the family.\n
\n23. If anyone deliberately broke a cooking pot or a gourd in a homestead, the purification ceremonies and sacrifices involved the slaughter of seven goats and sheep\n
\n24. If a man or woman fell down within their own homestead, purification and sacrifice were necessary.\n
\n25. If a bedstead broke when someone was sleeping in it, purification was required of the person.\n
\n26. No one might touch or approach the garbage dump (kiara) of a homestead other than the members of that homestead. If they did so, purification would be necessary.\n
\n27. If anyone, other than a child that had not been “born a second time,” or a very sick person, defecated within a hut or in the courtyard, a purification ceremony was essential.\n
\n28. It was taboo to come into contact with the menstrual blood of any other person (something which could happen easily in a hut), and purification was necessary if this happened. (There were certain minor exceptions).\n
\n29. In certain circumstances huts were pulled down and either left to rot or the materials stacked for future use; these circumstances were linked with death and divorce respectively.\n
\n30. It was taboo for any person including a child to die inside a hut. In the event of such an occurrence purification of all the inhabitants of the hut was necessary and the hut demolished.\n
\n31. If the child’s harness, ngoi was accidentally left outside overnight it must be beaten with a leather strap in the morning being asked, “where did you sleep?”\n
\n32. If the owner of a homestead cut himself and drew blood either while in the homestead or when he was out in the fields, he had to sacrifice a goat or sheep for purification.\n
\n33. If a hyena should enter a village or homestead and dung either in the open clearing of the entrance; area (thome) or in any courtyard (Nja), ceremonial purification was essential.\n
\n34. If a hyena should enter a hut, a purification ceremony must be performed.\n
\n35. If a jackal barked in the entrance area or in the courtyard of a homestead, a ceremonial purification was necessary.\n
\n36. Should any beast calf, goat, or sheep suck or lick any part of a human in a homestead, that animal had to be sacrificed for a purification ceremony at the village of a relation-in-law.\n
\n37. Should a toad, frog, or lizard fall or jump into the fire in the hearth of a hut, a purification ceremony was essential.\n
\n38. If an owl hooted near a homestead, or worse still, perched on any hut or granary, purification was necessary.\n
\n39. If a snake was killed within the confines of a homestead, a purification ceremony had to take place\n
\n40. It was taboo to kill a bird called (Cossypha or Robin chat), Kanyoni Kanja, within the confines of the homestead.\n
\n41. If a kite, when flying over a homestead, let its droppings fall on any person, that person had to be purified, the manner of purification depending upon the sex of the person involved.\n
\n42. Ni mugiro kugia na mambura ma uriri riria mundu wa hakuhi nawe akuite na hukuro ndiri irekwo,kana umite macakaya.NB gutiri mambura o mothe mekaguo riria mucii kwina gikuu\n
\n1. It\'s a taboo for a Kikuyu woman to get injured in the kitchen either by a knife or a cooking stone\n
\n2. It\'s a taboo for a Kikuyu man to hug his mother in law\n
\n3. It\'s a taboo for a Kikuyu man to spend a night in his in-laws home. Siku hizi GMOs wanalala na kukaa one week\n
\n4. It\'s a taboo for a Kikuyu man to carry a baby whether his own or otherwise\n
\n5. It\'s a taboo for a Kikuyu lady to take alcohol\n
\n6. It\'s a taboo for a Kikuyu man to taste alcohol before being introduced to it by his father \n
\n7. It\'s a taboo for a married woman to use her left hand to serve or give/ pass food to her husband. GMOs be advised that you should always use the right hand to serve a man\n
\n8. It\'s a taboo for a Kikuyu man to pass through a fence. A man should always use a gate and always ignore shortcuts\n
\n9. It\'s a taboo for a man to punish a girl named after his mother in law
\n10. It\'s a taboo for a married woman to abuse a child named after her father in law\n
\n11. It\'s a taboo for a married man to use his plain hands to discipline a child. A bare hand is for blessing a child and not for punishing. GMOs now know the reason that your mums always used a pair of slippers.\n
\n12. It\'s a taboo for a cooking stick to break during cooking\n
If you commit any of the above <i>mugiro</i>, you get <i>thahu</i> and finally kirumi and you should be cleansed .\n
    </string>
    <string name="kikuyu_calendar">
        <b>Mīeri Ya Ugīkūyū</b>\n

\n1.January – Mũgaa\n
2. February – Mũratho , Mùgetho? Themithu ?\n
3. March – Kĩhu (beginning of the Njahi season)\n
4. April – Mũratho, Muthatu kana Kibii\n
5. May – Mũgiranjara\n
6. June – Gathathanwa\n
7. July – Gathano\n
8. August – Mworianyoni\n
9. September – Mùga wa Kerì\n
10. October – Kĩhu 2 (Beginning of the Mwere season) Mwania Thenge\n
11. November – Kanyuahũngũ\n
12. December – Gatumu\n

        \n<b>MATHAA MA MUTHENYA WA GIKUYU</b> \n
\n1. Thinacara kinya thaa imwe ya Ruciini [6am to 7am] Riua rigicomoka Ngo-ini kana Riua rikiratha\n
2.Thaa imwe kinya thaa igiri cia Ruciini [7am to 8am] Riua riaratha kana Kiroko\n
3.Thaa igiri kinya thaa Ithatu cia Ruciini [8am to 9am] Ime Riatika kana Ikiongithia Njau\n
4.Thaa Ithatu kinya Thaa Inya [9am to 10am] Riahiuhia Ciande ,Mburi ikiumagara kana Igithii ruuru \n
5.Thaa Inya kinya thaa ithano [10am to 11am]Miaraho ya Ciuri\n
6.Thaa ithano kinya Thaa thita cia muthenya [11am to 12 noon] Igithii Ruui\n
7.Thaa Thita kinya Thaa Mugwanja [12 noon to 1pm] Miaraho,Riua Riegera kana Riua riehanda\n
8.Thaa mugwanja kinya Thaa inyanya [1pm to 2pm] Ikiuma Ruui\n
9.Thaa inyanya kinya Thaa kenda [2pm to 3pm] Miarahuko\n
10.Thaa kenda kinya Thaa Ikumi [2pm to 4pm ] Riua riarura kana Riua riaikia huho\n
11.Thaa Ikumi kinya Thaa ikumi na Imwe [4pm to 5pm] Mirugia Aka \n
12.Thaa ikumi na Imwe kinya Thinacara cia hwaiini[5pm to 6pm]Makenga Ariithi ,Mburi ikiinuka,Riua rigithua kana Riua rigicoka ngoiini\n
13.Thinacara kinya Thaa Imwe [6pm to 7 pm] Ngombe igikamwo kana Hwai-ini \n
14.Thaa Imwe kinya Thaa Igiri [7pm to 8pm]Kwagia mairia, Githuki Mundu kana Mburi ikiingira\n
15.Thaa Igiri kinya Thaa Ithatu [8pm to 9pm] Nyungu Yahagirwo\n
16.Thaa Ithatu kinya Thaa inya [9pm to 10pm] Ciekirwo Marigu na Nyeni\n
17.Thaa inya kinya Thaa Ithano [10pm to 11pm] Ikiihurwo\n
18.Thaa Ithano kinya Thaa thita [11pm 12midnight] Andu makoma kana Meigirira\n
19.Thaa Thita kinya Thaa Mugwanja [Midnight to 1am] Utuku Gatagati\n
20.Thaa mugwanja kinya Thaa Inyanya[1am to 2am]Andu Megarura\n
21.Thaa Inyanya kinya Thaa Kenda [2am to 3am] Ikiria Nyoni kana Ciumbani ikiinuka\n
22.Thaa Kenda kinya Thaa Ikumi [3am to 4am] Huho Njeke kana Ngwareiini\n
23.Thaa Ikumi kinya Thaa Ikumi na Imwe [4am to 5am] Nyoni Igicuracura ,Nyoni Ikigamba kana Riria Mara Ateire Nyina\n
24.Thaa Ikumi na Imwe kinya Thinacara cia Ruciini [5am to 6am] Ruoro rugitema\n
    </string>
    <string name="nyumba_na_thingira">
        \nIn any Kikuyu traditional homestead, the woman’s hut was the cradle of the family traditions and it loomed over the traditional homestead both in physical size and psychologically. The English word ‘house’ to the Kikuyu mind refers to any building, but ‘house’ in Kikuyu, Nyumba, in the context of a home is that which was built for a specific married woman as no two married women ever shared a house. The man’s habitation is a thingira and is properly what the word ‘hut’ conjures and it is improper to refer to the woman’s abode as ‘the woman’s hut’ as it cannot be a hut. To the Kikuyu mind, Nyumba, as a proper capitalized name always refers to the woman’s “house” and must be differentiated from a generic uncapitalised nyumba, which means any building. The man’s habitation is the thingira which however can never be capitalized as a proper name as there are many types of huts which lay claim to the name thingira like those built for young unmarried men or exclusively for goats but generally, a thingira is any habitation built for the exclusive use of the male gender. A nyumba in the context of a Kikuyu homestead refers to either a Nyumba or a thingira without distinction. Outside this context a nyumba means any building.\n
\nAs the Kikuyu were polygamous, a traditional homestead had several Nyumba as each wife had her own but only one man’s thingira. Circumcised but unmarried young men had their own young men’s thingira. Children and unmarried girls slept in the Nyumba. Girls and even children could distribute themselves in the various Nyumba and all the mothers were considered common to all. Every mother treated her co-wive’s children as her own and could feed and house them for the night if they fell asleep in her place listening to her fireside tales.\n
\nThese Nyumba were arranged around an open space, Nja that accommodated many outdoor activities especially food preparation. Each woman had a granary for her farm produce and they were all build near the entrance to this Nja with the first wife’s, nyakiambi being prominently nearest the entrance and the others supporting her. The man’s thingira was also built near the entrance slightly removed from the intimate conversation the various Nyumba made with the Nja. The first wife ruled this inner world, Nja and the homestead and the man was an appendage that had a stronger connection with the external world and the cattle krall, palisaded with a gate visible from the man’s thingira’s doorway. The first wife ruled this whole arrangement and because many of her activities, drying grain, pounding grain, cooking etc happened here, the female species acquired the name, Mundu-wa-Nja, or Person-of-the-Nja.\n
\nA nyumba can have only one door which normally faced the Nja though the man’s thingira had its door slightly askance from the courtyard. If there were young circumcised but unmarried men, with their own thingira it would never ever have a conversation with the Nja but would be located nearest the gate. After marriage young men were expected to move out of the homestead and establish their own.\n
\nThere were no partitions inside the man’s thingira and as you entered, you  found a raised platform on your right that was the bed of the man. Nearest the door to the head of the bed was placed on a platform, a barrel where the food for the man was placed for his convenience in case he was not in. Directly opposite the door was a goat fattening pen constructed in the same manner as in the woman’s hut. The left was left open for goats and sometimes a visitor’s bed. At the centre was a fireplace of three stones and it could sometimes be borrowed by the woman to cook an extra pot in the evening. On such an occasion she would sit in the thingira  tending the pot while a daughter tended her main fire and sat at her mother’s position. Other times she would join the man in the thingira when he had visitors. There was no firewood rack above the fire except a small rack over the doorway where the man kept saline earth for his goats\n
\nSeveral posts within the space but on the man’s side, kihanya would be used to hang his cloak, githii and leather bag. He would also keep his weapons, bow and arrow, spear and shield near him at the foot of his bed.\n
\nYoung men’s thingiras were arranged with sleeping beds on all three sides save the entrance and without a fattening pen. Sometimes young men from neighboring homesteads could share a thingira until they married and each established his own homestead. There was usually no fire inside the young men’s thingira, but rather an outside one.\n
\nDuring the day in the heat, the man seated on a stool would shelter under the shadow of the overhang just outside his door to the left or right. His walking stick would be beside him and if he entered inside he would go in and leave his walking stick next to the stool. If he left the compound he would carry the stick with him and sometimes even the stool. It was therefore easy for anyone to tell whether the man was in or away merely by the presence or absence of the walking stick and stool.\n
\nSometimes a young couple used the Nyumba for conjugal purposes but this would later become impractical and undesirable as the children grew older and then the function shifted to the thingira more so if he acquired many wives. Because Kikuyu men sometimes married as many as ten wives there is an interesting story as to how this rotation was managed.\n
\nWhen and why men began to live separately in a thingira is not on record, but it is a fact that a man cannot enter the Nyumba before all the children and animals have entered and everything has settled nicely. He MUST be the last to enter. The thingira may have started as a warm space to kill the time while as they say, “the chickens go in” and while waiting for the food to cook rather than waiting out in the cold or in the sometimes very noisy Nyumba exactly the function bars and clubs perform today. It could then have developed into a fully fledged habitation where he stayed permanently and entertained his friends. His presence in the Nyumba however remained with a symbolic stool which he rarely used.\n
\nThe thingira was where the man sat in the evenings in contemplation in front of a fire alone or with a friend and was rarely used during the day. The thingira was a quiet abode of contemplation, a retreat into the quiet uncluttered fundamental substance of life, – kanyumba ka meciria, something forever gone with the “wind of change”. The Nyumba was a noisy classroom.\n
    </string>
    <string name="urathi">
        \n<b>THE PROPHESIES</b>\n
1.There will come a people from the East who will look like butterflies. Their skins will be colourless like that of the tree frog, Kiengere and you will be able to see the blood flowing under their skins just like in the Ciengere (plural). These people will also look like lepers.\n
2.The Ciengere will cause a painful upheaval of the tribal ways and things will never be the same again. These pains will be the birth pangs of good and of bad.\n
3.An Iron snake will be built by the Ciengere from the Sea of Rukanga, iria ria cumbi, and it will enter the Sea of the Sparrow, iria ria ihii. It will not be possible to cut the snake with a machete or spear.\n
4.A living snake with a bushy head, kihinga, bellowing smoke will ride on top of the sleeping snake. It will swallow the Ciengere and spit them out.\n
5.Shortly after the snake’s coming, there will be a big famine and a pestilence that will nearly finish the people.\n
6.The Ciengere will carry sticks that spit fire and it will be foolish for our warriors to confront them with their spears.\n
7.The Ciengere will fill the whole land.\n
8.The Ciengere’s skin will look like they have leprosy and their eyes will have stripes like the skin of a mouse.\n
9.Children will be born who will not have ears but only holes. They will abandon the ways of the tribe and will show no respect to their elders and parents.\n
10.Children will be born who will wear bells, mbugi, in their ears and will not listen or hearken to tribal teaching, kirira.\n
11.Children will be born who will have no fear of committing abominable acts, migiro.\n
12.Adultery and promiscuity, waganu, will fill the whole land.\n
13.Theft and petty crime will fill the whole land.\n
14.Cooked food will be sold on roadsides and markets all over the country.\n
15.The Gikuyu people will not heed the leadership and warnings of the Anjiru Clan and instead will follow the Aicakamuyu.\n
16.Lake Naivasha will be planted with sugarcane and bananas by the Gikuyu.\n
17.The plains where the Maasai, Ukabi, roam with their cattle will be farmed and millet planted there.\n
18.The great forest of Mbage will one day join with the great one of Kiriti and will become one.\n
19.When the sleeping snake will shift and sleep alongside the Ngong Hills, only then will the living iron snake swallow the Ciengere and take them to the Sea of Rukanga.\n
20.Until the great Thingira wa Iregi (Ruling Council hut) shall be built in Githunguri kia Wairera and inaugurated with the necessary ceremonies and purification rites, the country will never be free of the ills brought by the Ciengere neither benefit from the good brought by them.\n
21.Until the great fig tree, Mugumo at Thika shall fall, the country, bururi, shall never be free.\n
\n<b>THE FULFILLMENT OF PROPHESY</b>\n
\nWhen I ask a young man whether he is hearing what I am saying with the earphones and ear buds ringing bells in his ears the answer is always an irritated, “Yes, I can hear you”\n
\nIn the time of Cege, all around Lake Naivasha was a paradise teaming with wildlife as if Noah’s ark had just been opened. It was not imaginable that the Gikuyu would one day live on the shores of Paradise Lost least of all plant bananas. The horrible implications of this prophesy is that one day the lake itself will be no more and will be farmland. Thai! Thathaiya Ngai Thai!\n
\nIt was unthinkable that cooked food could one day be sold. It was said that irio hiu itumaga mburi meaning that cooked food can never be sold. Traditionally the Gikuyu customs demanded that cooked food be shared freely.\n
\nIt is after all, the spirit of the Ciengere that will fill the whole land and not just the Ciengere themselves per se. Therefore we will see the youth transforming their skins, their hair and their ways to look like Ciengere. The Ciengere then will be everywhere.\n
\nThe railway linking the Kenyan Indian Ocean Coast and the Lake Victoria connected and united the new country in the name of Kenya and it would be impossible from then onwards to cut it up again into separate nations like existed before. The links are permanent and will never be broken. According to prophesy it cannot be cut.\n
\nIt is necessary in interpreting and decoding prophesy to go beyond the literal as many of the elements within a prophesy are but mere symbols. It is also necessary to understand that man is a microcosm of the universal events and therefore every human must at some time in his/her existence encounter a cataclysmic event that requires the rebuilding anew of the great Hut of the soul. Therefore even as we interpret Cege’s prophesies to have centred around the events of the coming of the white man and the railway, we see that we must not just behold a mere railway but the coming of a technological new age that will ensnare and swallow the youth for after all, the Mugumo with its roots in the underworld and that connected the Gikuyu to their ancestral past will have fallen. The event of the falling of the Great Mugumo tree at Thika was a decisive moment in the struggle for independence probably more so than the battles fought with arms. This was a spiritual struggle that involved the ancestors and the future generations and the white man seemed to understand this very well\n
\nWe must understand that the erection of the New Thingira, in every soul, in every home, not just the physical one at Githunguri or the one Mzee Jomo Kenyatta erected in Nairobi, holds the key to re-establishing the respect for the traditional prophetic Unjiru in us and the embracing of the futuristic and daring complexity of the Uicakamuyu in us. Every individual must have a connection to the past, the present and the future. The prophesied New Thingira must be erected spiritually for it to inaugurate the New Order in Gikuyu society, itwika. Prophesy is a clear vision of the future and destiny is therefore the living of prophesy not pre-ordainment. The destiny of the Gikuyu is to live the prophesy.\n
    </string>


    <string name="ngwiko_overview">Overview</string>
    <string name="ngwiko_organisation">Ngwiko</string>
    <string name="ngwiko_rules">Rules</string>
    <string name="ngwiko_taboos">Taboos</string>
    <string name="ngwiko_overview_text">
         \nAmong the things taught during the initiation period are the
matters relating to rules and regulations governing sexual indulgence. In order not to suppress entirely the normal sex instinct, the boys and girls are told that in order to keep good health they must acquire the technique of practising a certain restricted form of intercourse, called <i>umbani na ngwiko </i>(platonic love and fondling). This form of intimate contact between young people is considered right and proper and the very foundation stone upon which to build a race morally, physically and mentally sound.For it safeguards the youth from nervous and psychic adjustments.\n
   \nThe social life of Gikuyu youths covers a wide field of
activities. They organize numerous night and day dances for recreation and enjoyment. At these socials young men and women mix freely. It is generally at these social gatherings that friendship begins. A young man may attract the attention of a young girl, or girls, by his appearance, his smartness in dancing or dressing his hair, or by his charming and graceful carriage. Similarly a young girl may attract the attention of a young man, or men. The man who has several girl friends is known as <i>githaria</i> or <i>kiumbani</i> (heart-breaker).A Beau Brummel may attract as many as forty girls. A girl may win the admiration of several young men, but they would have to compete for her. The word <i>ngwiko</i> (fondling) is used in its real Gikuyu sense and not as the loose term <i>ngwiko ya gicomba</i>, employed by missionaries and detribalised Gikuyu, which means full sexual intercourse.\n
    \nIn a dance a <i>githaria</i> can easily be recognised, for he  dances with several girls around him, but in order that he  will not have a monopoly, a kind of Gikuyu " Paul Jones" dance, <i>guthombocana</i>, is repeated very often so as to allow the less attractive young men an opportunity of dancing with nice girls. Girls visit their boy-friends frequently, especially during the dancing seasons. The boys also visit the girls in their homes and take them to dances and escort them home afterwards.\n
    \n<i>Ngwiko</i>, or fondling, is looked upon as a sacred act and one which must be done in a systematic, well-organised manner. The Gikuyu do not kiss girls on the lips as Europeans do; therefore, <i>ngwiko</i> takes the place of lip kissing, but, unlike the Europeans, who are fond of kissing in public places, the Gikuyu consider such public display of affection vulgar. All matters relating to sex are done according to a well-regulated code of convention.\n
    </string>
    <string name="ngwiko_oragnisation_text">
        The girls visit their boy-friends at a special hut, <i>thingira</i>,used as a rendezvous by the young men and women. They bring with them their favourite food and drinks as a token of affection. These are shared among the age-group in the <i>thingira</i>, who eat their food collectively. No boy can eat or drink by himself what has been brought to him by his sweetheart;such an act would be severely punished. In this way the boys who have no girl-friends are included in all entertainment, because the good-looking young man of the age-group does not act for himself; his popularity is considered the popularity of the group as a whole, and his girl-friends are also regarded as friends of the members of the age-group.So no matter how ugly a boy may be,his ugliness is compensated for by the more attractive members of his age-group. There is a saying in Gikuyu :<i>"Mugikumia thaka, kumagiai ndoti ya riika ee hinya.Riika ritire gacii "</i>-(When you praise the handsome man,first praise an ugly and strong man of the age-group.There is no small or despised inferior man in the age-group).\n
    Girls may visit the <i>thingira</i> at any time, day or night.After eating, while engaged in conversation with the boys,one of the boys turns the talk dramatically to the subject of <i>ngwiko</i>. If there are more boys than girls, the girls are asked to select (<i>kuoha nyeki</i>) whom they want to have as their companion. The selection is done in the most liberal way.The language used is either in proverbs or indirectly as,for instance, the phrase" <i>Kuoha nyeki </i>-to tie the grass-which is equivalent to " Choose your partner." In such a case it is not necessary for the girls to select their own intimate friends, as this would be considered selfish and unsociable. Of course, this does not mean that the girls do not sometimes have <i>ngwiko</i> with those whom they are specially fond of, but generally they follow the rules of exchanging partners. The same freedom of social contact exists even among married people and for this reason youths are encouraged to cultivate the spirit of comradeship and group solidarity before marriage.\n
   \nAfter the partners have been arranged, one of the boys gets up, saying: "<i>Ndathie kwinogora</i>" (I am going to
stretch myseIf). His girl partner follows him to the bed.The boy removes all his clothing. The girl removes her upper garment, <i>nguo ya ngoro</i>, and retains her skirt, <i>muthuru</i>,and her soft leather apron, <i>mwengo</i>, which she pulls back between her legs and tucks in together with her leather skirt, <i>muthuru</i>.The two v-shaped tails of her <i>muthuru</i> are pulled forward between her legs from behind and fastened to the waist, thus keeping <i>mwengo</i> in position and forming an effective protection of her private parts. In this position the lovers lie together facing each other,with their legs interwoven to prevent any movement of their hips. They then begin to fondle each other, rubbing their breasts together, whilst at the same time they engage in love-making conversation until they gradually fall asleep. Sometimes the partners experience sexual relief,but this is not an essential feature of the <i>ngwiko</i>.The chief concern in this relationship is the enjoyment of the warmth of the breast, <i>urugare wa nyondo</i>, and not the full experience of sexual intercourse.\n
   \nIt has been said several times by Europeans, especially missionaries, that it is unbelievable that a young man and a young woman could sleep in one room, let alone in one bed, without copulating. Many Gikuyu have been punished and regarded as "sinners" by missionaries simply for having been found sleeping in the same room with a girl,for in their eyes such an act is sinful.\n
   \nThe Gikuyu who have not been brought up under the
missionaries\' influence find it difficult to understand "this sort of European puritanism, for a Gikuyu man has been taught from childhood to develop the technique of self-control in the matter of sex, which enables him to sleep in the same bed with a girl without necessarily having sexual intercourse;while the missionaries\' idea is, that since a white man would not be able to restrain himself under similar circumstances, so the African would not be able to,and so must be forbidden to sleep with a woman-friend in the Gikuyu fashion.\n
    </string>
    <string name="ngwiko_rules_text">
        The tribal law prohibits a young man from pulling out a girl\'s garment (<i>kugucia mwengu wa muiretu</i>) while having <i>ngwiko</i>, He must put his sexual organ between his thighs so as to prevent touching the girl with it. The custom also prevents a girl from touching the male sexual organ with her hands. Of course, it sometimes happens that in the case of a long-standing friendship a girl may allow a boy to put his sexual organ between her thighs and hold it tight in that position without penetrating;or by mutual arrangement a girl may allow her lover to have fuller intercourse, trusting that incomplete penetration would safeguard against the risk of conception.But such behaviour is absolutely against the tribal law and never takes place between casual lovers. If it does happen,which is rare, the law punishes it by imposing social stigma upon the offenders. Neither the man nor the girl can sleep with the back turned against the partner. The girl may not lie on top of the boy or across him (<i>gutagarara</i>); to do so,or to touch the man\'s penis, is" unclean" (<i>mugiro or thahu </i>),and both must be purified by a <i>mundu-mugo</i> (purifier).\n
   \nThe girl is expected to be a virgin in the sense of having an unperforated hymenal membrane when she marries. Any intercourse which may result in pregnancy before marriage is strictly forbidden. Any young man who may render a girl pregnant (<i>kohira moiretu ihu</i>) is severely punished by the <i>kiama</i> (tribal council). The fine for this is nine sheep or goats and three big, fat sheep (<i>ndurume</i>) as the <i>kiama</i> fees. Besides this, the man is made a social outcast or " sent to Coventry" (<i>kuhingwo</i>) by all the young men and girls of his own age-group.Punishment is also extended to the girl. She pays a fine by providing a feast to the men and the girls of her age-group. She is also liable to ridicule
(<i>kuhingwo and gucambio</i>).
   If a man is detected by a girl trying to loosen her garments during the night of <i>ngwiko</i> she generally reports the matter to all her friends in the district. The matter is taken to the age-group meeting (getungano kia riika). Such a man would be ostracised by his friends and would be debarred from having <i>ngwiko</i> with other girls, as they would not trust or have confidence in him. These guiding principles, ingrained in the very souls of the young men and women, serve as checks to sexual promiscuity, for, unless a man knows a girl very well, he would not run the risk of suggesting copulation to her lest she should not only refuse, but tell other girls and have him kuhingwo(" sent to Coventry").
    </string>
    <string name="ngwiko_taboos_text">

Between members of the same family all forms of erotic connection are considered a great sin. Although there is great freedom among young people in their courtship and
amorous experiments, brothers and sisters would not dare
to indulge in these activities in one another\'s presence.
In bachelor huts, where young people meet freely,brother
and sister cannot be present together at the same time,
except on purely social occasions when there is no sex-play.For example, if a brother knows that his sister has a lover in a particular bachelor-hut, he makes a point of not visiting the hut during the times when she is frequenting it. The same thing applies to the sister. This rule is also observed in dances and other ceremonies. No brother could take his sister, or any close female relative, as a partner on such occasions.During festival dances, where people from various districts meet and dance together, it is not always possible to recognise a relative who comes from far away,and a man may sometimes be seen dancing with his cousin by mistake. When this happens, people who know will start laughing and joking to warn the young man of his error. At once the two separate and find other partners, and sometimes a present is given to the girl by way of apology from the man.\n
   \nAll sexual familiarity between parents and their children is strictly forbidden.This applies to all children of the members of one\'s own age-grade, and breach of this rule is considered a great crime. This, of course, does not restrict parents .frorn teaching their children about sex. During early childhood parents talk freely to their children,explaining all matters connected with sexual taboos.\n
   \nIn the Gikuyu community any form of sexual intercourse other than the natural form, between men and women acting in a normal way, is out of the question. It is considered taboo even to have sexual intercourse with a woman in any position except the regular one, face to face.\n
\nBefore initiation it is considered right and proper for boys to practise masturbation as a preparation for their future sexual activities.Sometimes two or more boys compete in this, to see which can show himself more active than the rest. This practice takes place outside the homestead, under a tree or bush, where the boys are not visible to their elders. It is considered an indecency to be seen doing it, except by boys of the same age-grade.The practice is given up after the initiation ceremony, and anyone seen doing it after that would be looked upon as clinging to a babyish habit, and be laughed at, because owing to the free sex-play which is permitted among young people, there is now no need to indulge in it.\n
   \nMasturbation among girls is considered wrong, and if a girl is seen by her mother even so much as touching that part of her body she is at once told that she is doing wrong.It may be said that this, among other reasons, is probably the motive of trimming the clitoris, to prevent girls from developing sexual feelings around that point.\n
    \nOwing to these restrictions, the practice of homosexuality is unknown among the Gikuyu. The freedom of intercourse allowed between young people of opposite sex makes it unnecessary, and encourages them to acquire experience which will be useful in married life.\n
    </string>
    <string name="second_birth_text">
        Among the traditional Gikuyu, when a child was born, it took about three to four years sometimes even five for it to be weaned from its mother. The first separation of baby and mother was done by the midwife when she cut the umbilical cord. Between that first birth and the second, the mother carried the child everywhere she went and if need be had to carry it even on top of her other loads. On very very rare occasions would she let the child out of her sight and then only under an elder daughter and never with a co-wife or stranger. The child after it learnt how to walk always tagged behind its mother’s leather dress and usually would never let go and would hide between her legs under the long dress when a stranger was talking to the mother. The strong bond between child and mother was only broken after an elaborate ritual ceremony of the Second Birth also called “Returning the child into the womb”, Gucokia mwana ihu-ini.\n
\nThe Second Birth was important for several reasons.\n
\n1.Up to that point, about three to four years, the child’s Soul was in formation and could not take on any responsibility for sin. Any sin and the misfortune arising therefrom, thahu, was the parents’ responsibility and they were the ones who would undergo the purification ceremony for the sin, thahu. The Second Birth ceremony was therefore the real birth of the individual ego. Henceforth not only did the child become responsible for its own destiny but it shed any inherited sins of its parents.\n
\n2.It is after the ceremony that a child graduated from its first stage of child, mwana into becoming either a Kairitu, girl or a Kahii, boy. It does not mean he or she was a generic genderless being but he was a mwana wa kahii, and mwana wa kairitu. The child after that could be sent, for instance fetch such and such item from so and so.\n
\n3.The child and also the mother take the difficult step of disengaging themselves from each other. She could then have another child. Women who had children on top of each other before the previous had graduated were thought to be irresponsible women without planning and their husbands worse like they could not afford to have other wives. It was a planning thing.\n
\n4.The child could be allowed to sleep in another house away from the mother. Before that it could never be allowed to sleep out with relatives. Even more, the child could leave its mothers bed and sleep in the Kweru for a boy and in the girls’ bed, Kiriri for the girl. I say could because getting the privilege of sleeping in the girls’ bed, Kikiri required the consent of the older girls.\n
\nThe ceremony itself was a very elaborate affair and would take pages and pages to describe. I urge readers to get themselves a copy of Stanley Kiama Gathigira, Miikarire ya Agikuyu or Mathew Njoroge Kabetu Kirira kia Ugikuyu. Gathigira gives the Nyeri, Gaki version of the ceremony and Kabetu the Kabete version. Briefly, the ceremony required the use of the original half calabash that was used to wash the baby after it came from its mother’s womb and a new calabash, a fattened ram which the woman had to take to the river and have it dip its forelegs into, and eight leaves collected from the bush by children; four leaves of the Mukenia and four leaves of the Mutei for a total of eight leaves. The woman had to collect soil from the hoofsteps of the ram into the calabash. All these were brought to the man who then slaughtered the ram and its innards mixed with the soil. The child then dipped the leaves into the mix and smeared the mother. The highlight of the ceremony was an enactment of childbirth compete with labour pains. The intestines of the ram were tied between mother and child and the climax of the ceremony was the cutting of this ritual cord. After this, the woman and the child were clean shaven to look like the calabashes. The ceremony also involved the use of the four secondary spaces in a Gikuyu Nyumba, woman\’s house:Gaturwa-ini, Gaturi, Thegi, and Gicegu
    </string>
    <string name="marriage_stage1">
        Choice of Mates\n
In the Gikuyu community boys and girls are left free to choose their mates, without any interference on the part of the parents on either side. From earliest infancy there is close social intercourse between the sexes, which provides them with an opportunity of becoming acquainted with one another for a considerable time before courtship begins.Thus, hasty judgment in choosing one\'s husband or wife is almost out of the question.\n
\nFirst Stage\n
When a boy falls in love with a girl he cannot tell her directly that he loves her or display his devotion to her in public, as this would be regarded by the Gikuyu as impolite and uncultured. He therefore discusses the matter with one or two of his best friends in the age-group to which he belongs. They then all pay a visit to the girl\'s home. On their arrival at the girl\'s homestead they enter her mother\'s hut. The girl and her mother exchange greetings with them. The mother then offers them refreshment and immediately goes away. Now the boys and the girl are left alone. At this stage the conversation may start in the following manner:One of the boys addresses the girl:Mware wa Njuguna?" (Daughter of Njuguna), "Wouldn\'t
you like to ask us why we have come here to-night?"The girl answers: "No, it is not necessary to ask you that. Gikuyu custom provides that anyone passing by can come and have a meal with us."\n
 The boy: "That is right, Mware wa Njuguna, but we are looking for a homestead where we could be adopted and be given food and shelter not only when we are passing by, but as children of the homestead."\n
  At this remark the girl at once knows their object, and she asks them to state definitely which one of them is looking for the adoption. The boy then points out his friend who is in love with the girl. If she accepts him as her future husband she tells them to go away and come back some other time. Sometimes two or three visits of this kind are made. When she gives her final answer, she says to them:" I am willing that the son of So-and-so should be adopted into our homestead, but the ceremonial side of it is a matter for my parents. You had better talk to them about it yourselves."\n
   If she does not accept him, she says: "Our house is not big enough to adopt anyone at present," and they go away.
    </string>
    <string name="marriage_stage2">
If accepted, her lover goes home and reports the matter to his parents. They then prepare honey or sugar-cane beer, which they take to the girl\'s parents. It is carried in two calabashes, one big and the other small. This beer is known as njohi ya njoorio, i.e. "The beer of asking the girl\'s hand." When the parents of the two parties meet, the first thing the girl\'s parents do is to provide the visitors with food before
they go into the question of matrimony. After this they state the object of their visit, but most of the conversation regarding their future son- or daughter-in-law is carried on in proverbs. The girl is called and, after being introduced, she is asked if she has agreed to become engaged, As she cannot answer directly yes or no, a little ceremony is necessary. Therefore, she is asked gently to fetch a particular horn used for beer-drinking;then to fill it with beer and hand it to her father who, after sipping a little and spitting it out, sprinkles some on his chest. He then hands it over to his wife who does the same. The horn is filled a second time and is handed to the boy\'s parents who repeat the same procedure. In each case the girl takes a sip first as a sign of consent.\n
   \nIf the lover has been refused he reports to his parents who, if they would like their son to marry the girl, may visit the girl\'s parents. The same ceremony takes place, but if the girl disapproves of it she will not pour out the beer or take the first sip. The visiting parents then go away.\n
    \nWhen the parents\' initial ceremony is concluded and the girl is willing to be engaged, close friends are invited and the beer is shared among them. At the conclusion of this friendly gathering they all join in a prayer, kurathimithia,uttering blessings for the future unity and progress of the two families.
    </string>
    <string name="marriage_stage3">
When the boy\'s parents return home they begin to collect sheep and goats, or cattle if they are rich, for the first instalment of the dowry, ruracio , these would be taken by the lover to the girl\'s homestead and led to the hut of the girl\'s mother. This visit is followed by another in which some beer is brought, and the girl is consulted as in the first VISit. This beer is called njohi ya guthugumitheria mburi, i.e. the beer for blessing the ruracio sheep and goats. This instalment is followed by another in a few days, and so on until the number of animals amounts to about thirty or forty. Beer is not necessarily brought each time. Even if a man is rich it is considered ill-luck to bring all the ruracio at once. When, according to the custom of the clan, the amount required for sealing the engagement has been sent, a day is fixed for the actual engagement ceremony, called ngurario, i.e. pouring out the blood of unity. In this all the relatives are called to the girl\'s homestead, where a sumptuous feast is provided, which includes the slaughtering of one fat sheep (ngoima ya ngurario) which has been sent from the boy\'s homestead specially for this purpose.\n
    \nThe significance of this ceremony is in the first place to announce publicly that the girl is engaged; secondly, to provide the relatives on both sides with an opportunity of meeting and getting to know one another; and, thirdly, to decide on how much the ruracio should be. The amount varies from one clan to another and from district to district, although the amount required by the Gikuyu law is thirty sheep and goats. Sometimes, however, it runs to between thirty and eighty sheep and goats, apart from numerous presents exchanged on both sides. When a cow is included in the ruracio it is valued at ten sheep and goats, while an ox is valued at five sheep and goats.\n
   \n The main feature of this ceremony consists in the killing of a fat sheep kept for this purpose. The sheep must be of a certain colour-black,white or brown-inkeeping with the symbolism adhered to for ritual purposes by the particular clan concerned. The blood is sprinkled along the gateway and towards Mount" Kenya (Kere-Nyaga);the contents of the stomach are also sprinkled in the same way,and also on the sheep and goats or cattle which have been brought in for the ruracio. This signifies that they are now purified and protected from any evils, and that the boy\'s parents have presented them to the girl\'s parents as a sign of good faith. From this time on the interests of the two clans are closely linked.
    </string>
    <string name="marriage_stage4">
 After all the arrangements are made in regard to ruracio, the maturity of the girl is discussed. The boy\'s parents say to the girl\'s parents: "Is your daughter grown-up? "-meaning: "Has she menstruated yet?"At the end of the discussion a final day is fixed on which to sign the marriage contract. On the day in question all representatives of the two clans and friends are invited. They bring with them plenty of food and drink for the feast. The ceremony,which is called guthenja ngoima, consists of slaughtering six fat sheep, and in case of a rich man, an ox and five sheep.In doing this the girl\'s consent must be obtained. She is asked to provide the knife for skinning the sheep and to take a leading part in slaughtering the first animal. The kidneys of the first sheep are roasted and served to the bride-to-be, who eats them, indicating in this way that the engagement still holds good and that the families can proceed with the formality of signing the marriage contract.\n
\nWhen this is done, the people assemble and take part in the feast. This is followed by a big dance and the singing of songs. The boy, with his age-group, comes in procession, carrying special presents for the girl\'s mother and for the members of her clan. Any property, such as an axe,basket or large leather strap, which the girl may have lost as a child, will be made up to her parents by these presents.\n
\nAt about sunset, after the casual visitors have gone, the women representatives of the clan are called into the yard where baskets are kept containing their presents. These presents are contributed by one of the elders, while the womenfolk cheer every recipient with great excitement. This is followed by a dance and song, called gitiro, for women only, which marks the end of the ngoima ceremony.\n
  \n If the boy\'s homestead is in the neighbourhood, a short visit is paid by a group of women, taking with them presents for the boy\'s relatives, but if the homestead is far away the visit is left to a later date. From this time onward the girl is regarded as having been blessed and given away to the boy\'s clan by her parents in agreement with the whole clan. She can now go and weed gardens with the boy\'s mother and other relatives in company with her girl-friends. The function of the ngoima ceremony is to furnish a public wedding celebration in which all marriage agreements are concluded and in which the girl is betrothed t6 her fiance, not only by her parents, but by the representative body of the clan acting collectively. She can now be taken to the boy\'s home as his wife at any time, without any further ceremony being performed at her parents\' homestead.
    </string>
    <string name="wedding_day">
 When the boy has provided himself with a hut and made the necessary preparation for housekeeping, he approaches his parents, especially his mother, and asks them to arrange a special day suitable for bringing his wife home. The arrangement is made according to certain propitious days of the moon, in accordance with the clan\'s history and traditions.For instance, many clans may not hold any wedding between the old and new moon, since this period is regarded as a " dark period" (mweri we nduma).The period preferable for embarking on any important project is the interval between the new moon and the full moon.\n
  \n A Gikuyu wedding is a thing which baffles many outsiders and terrifies many Europeans who may have an opportunity of witnessing the events. This wedding drama misleads foreign onlookers, who do not understand the Gikuyu custom, into thinking that the girls are forced to marry, and even that they are treated as chattels.\n
 \n  In response to the boy\'s request, the family meets in council; the day is fixed for the wedding and kept secret from the girl-thusadding a dramatic touch to the proceedings. On the wedding day the boy\'s female relatives set out to watch the girl\'s movements.She might be in a garden, weeding, or in a forest collecting firewood, etc.When they have obtained the necessary information as to where she is working they search for her. On finding her they return with her, carrying her shoulder-high.This is a moment of real theatrical acting. The girl struggles and refuses to go with them, protesting loudly and even seeming to shed tears, while the women giggle joyously and cheer her with songs and dances. The cries and cheers can be heard for miles around, and the Gikuyu people will know that the son of So-and-so has taken the daughter of So-and-so in marriage while foreigners may imagine that the girl has been forcibly seized. It is probable that any person
who is not well acquainted with the Gikuyu customs may easily mistake the drama for reality.\n
  \n In some cases, where the families are large, a counterfeit fight is staged between the women of both sides. This provides great entertainment for the women and is followed by a liberal feast at the bridegroom\'s homestead. The girl\'s cries, which are uttered theatrically in a singing manner, include such phrases as: "I do not want to get married! I will kill myself if you take me away from my parents! Oh! How foolish I was to leave my home alone and put myself into the hands of merciless people! Where are my relatives? Cannot they come and release me and prevent my being taken to a man whom I do not love? ..and so on. This goes on until the girl reaches the boy\'s homestead, where she is led into her new hut, while children greet her, singing praises for their new bride. On her way home the bride is cheered by passers-by, who utter blessings for the bride and bridegroom and for their future homestead.\n
   \n After the bride is comfortably settled in her new hut, the whole party of women from both clans, who a short while ago were engaged in a mock fight, join together and start dancing, singing and cheering hilariously. In the evening the bride is visited by her age-group of both sexes, who bring presents in way of food and ornaments. The bride entertains them with songs called !cerero, i.e. "weeping," in which girls only take part while the boys listen. The kerero songs are mostly connected with the collective activities of the girl\'s age-group, and the part played by the girl. It is considered as the age-group mourning for the loss of the services and companionship of one of their number who, by marriage, has passed to another age-group.\n
    The mourning songs are continued for eight days, during which time the bride is frequently visited by her friends and age-group of both sexes.\n
    \n During this period the bride may not go out publicly or do any work. She has a special back path which she may use when she leaves the hut during the day to sit under a tree for fresh air. Her girl-friends keep her company, together with the children of the family. The kerero goes on the whole day and a part of the evening, except for a few intervals between the arrival and departure of the visitors. About ten o\'clock in the evening the bride and bridegroom are left to themselves until the neighbourhood of nine o\'clock next morning, when the visitors begin to pour\n
\nVirginity\n
    \nThe question of physical virginity (as stated in the chapter dealing with the female circumcision) is very important, and parents expect their daughters to go to their husbands as physical virgins. This must be reported to the parents of both sides. The boy has to show by certain signs that the girl was a virgin; the girl, too, has to do the same to show that the boy is physically fit to be a husband. "In case of impotency on either side, the matter is put before the families\' council and the marriage is annulled at once.\n
    \nOn the eighth day, when the kerero ceases, a sheep is killed, the fat of which is fried and the oil is used to anoint  the bride in a ceremony of adoption into the new clan.After she has been admitted as a full member of the husband\'s family, she is free to mingle with its members  and take an active part in the general work of the homestead. When the adoption ceremony is concluded, a day is fixed immediately for her to pay a visit to her own parents. Care is taken in appointing the day, for she must not travel or cook during her menstrual period.On this particular visit she carries a small calabash with beer in it for the use of her parents in blessing her. On her way she is led by a small girl, who goes before her holding one end of a stick, the other end of which is held by the bride, who follows as though she were blind. She is supposed to be unable to see, and may not speak with any stranger she may meet during her journey. She goes all the way with bent head, hiding her face shyly, especially when somebody passes by her. She returns hack in the evening (if the
parents are in the neighbourhood) with presents from her parents. Sometimes when parents are rich she is given two or three sheep or goats. Her father-in-law also gives her presents; these vary in some cases from five sheep and goats to ten or a cow and a piece of fertile land. These presents are regarded as an act of " warming" the bride\'s hut, and they end the marriage ceremonial.\n
   \n<b>Mihitwa ya kihiko</b>\n
1. Mwihitwa wa nituguturia ndugu na urata - Nyama yaguo ni kiande/guoko\n
2. Guturia gikeno thiini wa mucii witu - Nyama yaguo ni mbaru (ikengeto) \n
3. Kuinuka na mburungo/kwaura,kuihurira rwiga,kuara uriri - Gitungo kia mara\n
4. Guturia thayu - Ini\n
5. Cia mucii ti como/ci uriririithiragira uriri cia mucii itikiraga muhaka - higo\n
6. Guturia utheru- nja ni ya muthuri nyumba ni ya mutumia - wei ni wa mutumia\n
7. Tutikarua mbara cia uriri/mbu ya thaa kenda ndietikaguo - kinina muku(ruhonge)- iriyaguo ni mutumia tu\n
8. Ni ndigwathaga wega nawe nindigwathikagira - matu - mariyaguo ni mutumia\n
9. Kiimba kia muthoni na muthoni giturage hamwe - Ngaii\n

    </string>
    <string name="wedding_day_label">Wedding Day</string>
    <string name="marriage_stages">Marriage Stages</string>
    <string-array name="stages">
        <item>First Stage</item>
        <item>Second Stage</item>
        <item>Third Stage</item>
        <item>Forth Stage</item>
    </string-array>


    <string name="man_stages">Man Life</string>
    <string name="woman_stages">Woman Life</string>

    <string name="woman_stages_details">
        MUNDU-WA-NJA\n
\nThe general term for a woman is mutumia, meaning ‘one whose lips are sealed’ and the name for the female gender is Mundu-wa-nja meaning ‘Person of the Nja’. The Nja was the open courtyard space surrounded by all the huts in a homestead. The Gikuyu were polygamous and each woman in a homestead had her own hut, nyumba and the man his own hut, thingira. Each woman also had her own granary and all these structures were held together by the Nja. The Nja was bare earth and always swept clean and it was taboo for someone to trip and fall within it. It meant there were things lying around loosely. The swept Nja also made it difficult for snakes and other small animals to venture there. The food preparation and cooking also happened in the Nja when weather permitted and the inside of the hut was used mainly in the evenings and at night.\n
\nThe woman ruled the Nja and this was her realm. The man usually would sit outside his thingira or with friends around another fireplace near the entrance to the courtyard, boi-ini. Cattle were not allowed into the Nja and  though goats were permitted they were controlled in a corner of the Nja by providing sweet potato vines hung on a post, Kihanya. They were also provided with a trough filled with saline earth for them to lick therefore they could not roam about the Nja. Cow peas, millet, sorghum and other produce would also be spread out to dry in the Nja and because of this the beloved small robin bird, Kanyoni-ka-nja or ‘Bird of the Nja’ was always about moving around and feeding on the seeds. Like the small bird moving up and about in the Nja, the woman was also the ‘Person of the Nja‘, Mundu-wa-nja, the name for the feminine gender. And just as all the built objects in a Gikuyu homestead orbit the Nja, so does the woman act as a central force holding the members of a Gikuyu family in place. The Nja is a mirror of her world.\n
\nMUNDU-MUKA\n
\nThis name Mundu-muka is used in the Gikuyu Bible for ‘woman’. It means ‘the person who came’ (from uka-come). When a woman married a man she is the one who left her people and joined her husband’s people, thus she gained the name mundu-muka or ‘the one who came’. But this was not the way things worked at the beginning of time. Gikuyu myths talk of a time when the woman was the head of the household and it was the man who came to her and was married to her just like in the case of the original nine plus one daughters but that is another story.\n
\nNGATHA\n
\nNgatha ya Mutumia is a prosperous woman of substance of the Nyakinyua or Makanga grade. Traditionally the picture of a Ngatha was not one of a thin woman like the Ngatha of today as Mrs.Jane Kiano nor  was it of a fiery-brand like a  Mrs.Wambui Otieno or a Wangari Maathai but one of quiet self-assurance and confidence with just a hint of disdain. Mama Ngina Kenyatta is the true personification of a Gikuyu ngatha. She is ample and has the overpowering presence of a queen yet is still a Mutumia, a woman of discretion. The Catholics try to pass off the virgin Mary as a Ngatha but that picture is riddled with contradiction as their Mary is first and foremost an innocent virgin most usually depicted as being at the level of a maiden, muiritu gathirange. Ngatha ya mutumia is rare and at a spiritual level this is what every woman strives to be whatever her outward circumstances may be. It is not dependent on adulation but  on an inner experience and sense of self satisfied well-being. Gwikindira.\n
    </string>

    <string name="council_stages">Councils</string>
    <string name="council_stage1">Before a boy goes through circumcision ceremony he is considered as a mere child, and as such has no responsibility in the tribal organisation; his parents are responsible for all his actions. If he commits any crime he cannot be prosecuted personally, it is his parents\' duty to answer for him. But this liberty ceases immediately he is circumcised, because he is now" full grown," and has assumed the title of mûndû-mûrûme (a he-man), and as such he must share the responsibility with other" he-men" (arûme).\n
 \nAs soon as his circumcision wound heals he joins in the national council of junior warriors, <i>njama ya anake a mumo</i>, At this stage his father provides him with necessary weapons, namely, spear, shield, and sword; then a sheep or a male goat is given to the senior warriors of the district, who receive it in the name of the whole national council of senior warriors.The animal is killed for a ceremony of introducing the young warrior into the general activities and the etiquette of the warrior class.\n
    \nIn former days the ceremony was more elaborated, the weapons of the young warrior were sprinkled with the blood of the ceremonial animal, then the leading warrior shouted a war-cry (ruhio), his companions stood up brandishing their spears and lifting their shields upwards; and in a ritual tone they chanted in unison the following warrior\'s resolution (mwihitwa wa anake):\n
 "We brandish our spears, which is the symbol of our courageous and fighting spirit, never to retreat or abandon our hope, or run away from our comrades. If ever we shall make a decision, nothing will change us; and even if the heaven should hold over us a threat to fall and crush us, we shall take our spears and prop it. And if there seem to be a unity between the heaven and the earth to destroy us, we shall sink the bottom part of our spear on the earth, preventing them from uniting; thus keeping the two entities, the earth and the sky, though together, apart. Our faith and our decision never changing shall act as balance."\n
 After this ceremony all joined in the meat feasting, and a mock fight was arranged to test the skill of the young warrior. This initiation gave the young warrior the privilege of participating in all warrior\
        \'s dances and songs; but he was not yet allowed to perform or to appear inside the circle, this being reserved for the senior warriors.</string>
    <string name="council_stage2">
             The second stage in warrior-hood was celebrated about eighty-two moons or twelve rain seasons following the circumcision ceremony. At this juncture the junior
warrior was promoted to the council of senior warriors, <i>njama ya ita</i> (war council). The initiation fee to this rank was two sheep or goats, there was no ritual performed at this stage, but the animals were slaughtered and eaten in a general meat feast. Immediately after this, the candidate was taken to a big dance, and introduced to the higher rank inside the circle of the dance. There he was proclaimed as having reached the status of senior warriors.\n
 \nFrom the governmental point of view the whole of the warrior class, composed of several age-groups, was divided into two sections, from which the two councils of senior and junior warriors were formed. Each group had its village, district and national leaders (athamaki a riilca), who acted as spokesmen in all matters concerning the welfare of the groups and the tribe. These leaders were chosen by their particular groups at general or public assembly. They were men who had proved by their own actions, their capability of leadership;had shown bravery in wars,impartiality in justice, self-sacrifice, and above all, discipline in the group. A man with these qualities was able to attain a high position and esteem in the community, especially when he had retired from the activities of a warrior. Judges and responsible elders, as we shall see later, were chosen from such men.\n
\nThe principles of the warriors\' organisation, such as age-grading and the etiquette of general behaviour, are still adhered to inside the Gikuyu country, but owing to the liquidation of military exercises, which was the main function of the warrior class as the defence force of the country, the warriors\' organisation has lost the significance which it used to have in former days.
    </string>
    <string name="council_stage3" >
        The third stage in manhood is marriage. When, a man has married and has established his own homestead, he is required to join the council of elders (kiama); he pays one male goat or sheep and then he is initiated into a first grade of eldership (<i>kiama gia kamatimu</i>), the word matimu; which means spears, signifies the carriers of spears, which denotes the warriors who have joined the kiama while still functioning as warriors, and who are carrying spears because they have not yet been given the staff of office.They are not yet elders, they are learners of the kiama\'s procedures. The <i>kamatimu</i> act as messengers to the kiama, and help to skin animals, to light fires, to bring firewood, to roast meat for the senior elders, and to carry ceremonial articles to and from the kiama assemblies. They must not eat kidneys, spleen, or loin, for these are reserved for the senior elders. Any <i>kamatimu</i> who dares eat one of these portions from a ceremonial animal is fined a ram, which is killed to purify the offender and at the same time to initiate him into the secret of the higher grade of eldership.
    </string>
    <string name="council_stage4" >
Next to <i>kamatimu</i> comes kîama kîa mataathi, i.e. the council of peace, this stage is reached when a man has a son or daughter old enough to be circumcised. Before the child enters in the circumcision ceremony, the father is called upon by the kîama kîa mataathi of his village, and asked to prepare himself for a ceremony called gûtonyio kerera, that is, to be initiated into the core of the tribal tradition and custom. The initiate then consults a diviner or a seer to predict a suitable date for the ritual; finally, a day is fixed according to the prediction. The senior elders of the district are invited to attend the ceremony at the candidate\'s homestead.\n
    \nOn the day appointed, the elders of ceremonial rank assemble and sit down in a circle outside the hut, or huts; here they are welcomed by the candidate and his wife, or wives. After exchanging greetings, food and drink are brought to them, for they must first satisfy their hunger before entering into ritual acts. Two of the elders are appointed to act as officiating priests.\n
  \n The chosen elders, carrying their staff of office, mûthegi, and sacred leaves, mataathi, enter in the hut where they are welcomed by the candidate and his senior wife, whose child is about to be circumcised. A small calabash filled with honey or sugar-cane beer is handed to them by the man, while his wife gives them a small drinking-horn.Four of them sit round the fireplace in the centre of the hut. One of the elders fills the horn with the beer, he takes a sip and spits over his right and left shoulders; then he pours out the beer over the three stones which support a cooking-pot over the fire; at the same time the officiating elder calls upon the ancestral spirits to commune with them.The horn is filled a second time and, after the leading elders have taken a sip each, the horn is handed over to the man who sips and then passes it to his wife. In a low and ritual tone, all (our join in chanting a prayer, saying: \n
"May our child grow well and live to pass this ceremony with joy and prosperity; may our child live to be father (or mother) of many healthy children and thereby perpetuate our family group."\n
    \nWhen the preliminary ceremony is. completed, the candidate and his wife are sworn to keep the secret of the kîama, and never to reveal it to anyone who is not ritually initiated into the age-grade of the kîama kîa mataathi,It is only when they have taken this solemn oath that the secret matters and the procedure, including the etiquettes of the Peace Council, are revealed to them. This done,the candidate is led outside to be introduced to the assembled elders. He walks between the two officiating elders, his wife following behind them carrying a big calabash of beer.
The small procession enters into the circle. Here the candidate is greeted ceremonially, to the elders he says:\n
" Wanyuwakine"(" my equals");the elders answer:" Wanyuwakine" (" our equal "). \n
This form of greeting is only exchanged by those who are politically, religiously,and socially equals.The salutation signifies that the candidate has been accepted as a full member of the peace council, he now sits in the circle in that capacity.\n
    \nImmediately one of the elders takes the beer and fills a drinking horn with it. He stands facing Kiri-Nyaga (Mount Kenya), and calls upon Ngai (God) to give them peace, wisdom and prosperity, and to bless the candidate and his homestead.The rest of the elders lift up their staffs (mîthîgi), and answer in chorus, saying: "Peace, peace, beseech Ngai, peace be with us, peace." After this the candidate is invested with his staff of office (mûthigi) and a bunch of sacred leaves (mataathi). This signifies that he is now a peaceful man, that he is no longer a carrier of spear and shield, or a pursuer of the vanity of war and plunder. That he has now attained a stage where he has
to take the responsibility of carrying the symbols of peace and to assume the duty of peace-maker in the community.\n
    \nAt the end of the ceremony of installing the candidate in the status of the kîama kîa mataathi, a male goat is slaughtered, its blood is poured at the entrance of the homestead,the contents of the stomach are sprinkled at the entrance of the hut and in the compound to keep the evil spirits away.\n
 Finally, the sexual organ of the goat is dipped in the contents of the stomach, then it is slit and worn as a bracelet on the right wrist of the candidate. This is a pledge of calmness, for the sexual organ is considered as the driving factor in fierceness, and having been symbolically cut away and placed on the wrist, the man is thereby expected to be guided by reason and wisdom, and not by emotion. The ceremony is concluded with a big feast of beer and meat and other edibles-atthis feast elders and their wives join in singing ceremonial songs.
    </string>
    <string name="council_stage5" >
        The last and most honoured status in the man\'s life history is the <i>kîama kîa maturanguru</i> (religious and sacrificial council). This stage is reached when a man has had practically all his children circumcised, and his wife (or wives) has passed the child-bearing age. At this stage the man has passed through all age-grades, has been initiated to them all. Apart from his staff of office, he wears brass rings (icûhî) in his ears, but he is not yet invested with the power to lead a sacrificial ceremony at the sacred tree (mûgumo mûtî wa igongona). To acquire this privilege he has to pay a ewe. This is taken to the sacred tree where the animal is slaughtered by the elders of the sacrificial council. This ceremony is performed in secrecy and only by the selected few who are fortunate enough to live to that esteemed age. No one outside the members of the sacrificial council is allowed anywhere near the sacred tree when this ceremony is in progress. Half of the animal is eaten by the elders and the other half is burnt in the sacrificial fire. The main feature of this ceremony is dedication of the man\'s life to Ngai (God) and to the welfare of the community. What actually happens at the sacred tree with regard to preparation of the ceremony is very hard to say, for the writer has not had the opportunity of attending the ceremony, having not yet reached the required age. But he had the privilege of watching the elders going to and from the sacred tree while herding sheep and goats near the ceremonial grove called mogumo wa Njathi.\n
    On coming out from the sacred tree the elders carry bunches of sacred leaves called maturanguru. The elders of this grade assume a role of" holy men." They are the high priests. All religious and ethical ceremonies are in their hands.
    </string>
    <string name="gakenge">A new born baby for the first few months or so. After that he is referred to as Kaana, baby. Major ceremony – Being born, gūciarwo kwa mwana.</string>
    <string name="kahii">A young boy floricking about like a young kid goat. major ceremony – The second Birth, gūcokia mwana ihu-iinī</string>
    <string name="kihii">A big boy nearing circumcision which would be anything from 12 to 18 years. To be called a Kīhīī (Kīhīī gīkī), is an insult as it is a reference to the fact that one is due or overdue for “straightening” – nī ūtigītie handū.</string>
    <string name="mumo">Literally means “coming out”, “emerging” like a butterfly from a cocoon into the full broom of God’s creation. Circumcision ceremonies – These were the most important of the Gikūyū ceremonies of becoming. Mambura ma irua.</string>
    <string name="mwanake">A young man until marriage. God’s material creation in its full glory. God, Ngai, did not create a child but a fully grown man. A young man is literally God’s fragment that was fashioned into a man by the creator, Mūmbi. Mwanake nī kīenyū kīa Ngai. Mwanake wa Njaama ya ita is a member of the warrior coupes, military.  Mwanake wa Njaama ya kamatimū is a member of the policing and guard coupes, Police.</string>
    <string name="muthuri">Married man who can still be called upon to serve military duty in a major war.</string>
    <string name="muthuri_kiama">An elder who serves in one or more of the many Councils. Because the Gikuyu system of government had no chiefs or kings, all government was through consensus in the various tribal Councils. Some were standing Councils with a membership representing the various clans. Other Councils were constituted on demand. To be a member of a Council was through the payment of a goat to the Council.Elders do not serve in the military or police coupes.</string>
    <string name="muiru">mutumia kuuma wa gatatu guthii na mbere (nyakiambi,nyakiamburi na muiru othe metanaga airu). The head wife (nyakiambi) has no superior authority over the rest. But she is only respected for her seniority in age, providing that she lives up to it.</string>
    <string name="muthuri_wakwa">Each wife addresses her husband as Mûthuuri wakwa (elder mine or my husband) and collectively as Mûthuuri witû</string>
    <string name="mutumia">This is how the husband addresses his wife. Collectively he addresses them as atumia akwa (ladies mine). They address him collectively as mûthuri witû (elder ours).This form of address is extended symbolically to each member of the husband\'s age-grade. And he, too, addresses the wives of the members of his age-grade in the same manner as \" lady or ladies mine.\"</string>
    <string name="husband_bother">He is given a nickname as a sign of endearment. He, too, reciprocates in the same way, and sometimes a present is necessary as a sign of naming.</string>
    <string name="maramu">This is how the sister of the wife is addressed by the husband, which is something like\" my sister-in-law.\" All the wife\'s other relatives, including her parents, are addressed individually as mûthoni wakwa, and collectively, athoni akwa, i.e. my relative-in-law and relatives-in-law respectively.</string>
    <string name="husband_parent">The wife addresses the husband\'s parents as maitû or baba; i.e. my father or mother, as case may be. They address her by her father\'s name as daughter of So-and-so, this is a sign of endearment and respect to the parents.</string>
    <string name="children_of_the_same_mother"><![CDATA[Male children address one another as <b>mûrû wa maitû</b>, i.e. son of our mother. Female children address one another as <b>mwarî wa maitû</b> (daughter of my or our mother). A brother refers to his sister as <b>mwarî wa maitû</b>, and the sister to his brother as <b>mûrû wa maitu</b>.\\n     \\nAs regard to seniority in age, the elder child is addressed by the younger one as <b>mûkûrû wakwa</b> (my senior), the parents refer to such a child as <b>irigithathi</b> (first child). The first-born is regarded as a centre of affections and a precious possession of the parents, especially that of the first wife.\\n \\nThe younger child is addressed by the elder one as <b>mûruna wakwa</b> (my follower or one who followed me). The last child is known as <b>kîhinga nda</b> (one who closed the womb),such a child is held dear, particularly by the mother.]]></string>
    <string name="children_of_one_father"><![CDATA[The relation between the children of one father and different mothers is strengthened by the father. They address one another as <b>mûrû wa baba</b> (son of our father), <b>mwarî wa baba</b> (daughter of our father).]]></string>
    <string name="children_of_the_same_mother_and_father">The bond of kinship between the children of the same mother and father is stronger than that of the children of one father and different mothers. The feeling between the former is that of inseparables, and it is said that, having slept in the same womb (maraire nda îmwe), and having suckled the same breast (mongire nyondo îmwe), they are one another\'s flesh and blood, and as such they ought to live for one another.</string>
    <string name="fathers_brothers"><![CDATA[All the brothers are addressed by his brother\\’s children by the name of\" baba witû (father ours),\" according to their age in comparison to that of the real father. If it be an elder brother he is addressed as <b>baba mûkûrû</b> (elder father,my or our), the younger brother is called <b>baba mûnyinyi</b> (small or younger father, my or ours). They in turn address the children in the same way as their own. Sometimes these relations depend on the position of the fathers, if they are rich and entertain the children nicely they hear more of \" our elder father, our younger father,\" but if they are not in a position to give the children treats, they hear less of the beloved form of address. Hence a Gikuyu saying that <b>\"Mûtheni ndetagwo baba mûkûrû kana mûnyinyi,\" </b>that is, a poor man does not command the respect of being called\" elder or younger father.\"]]></string>
    <string name="children_of_brothers"><![CDATA[The form of address used between the children of brothers is that of <b>mûrû or mwarî wa baba mûkûrû or mûnyinyi</b> (son or daughter of my or our elder or younger father, as the case may be).]]></string>
    <string name="Sister_of_the_father"><![CDATA[Sister of the father is called <b>tata</b> (aunt), the relation between her and her brother\'s children depends mostly on whom she marries and the distance between her husband\'s homestead and that of the brother.]]></string>
    <string name="aunts_children"><![CDATA[Aunt\\’s children and those of her brothers address one another as <b>mûihwa</b> (cousins), there is a strong bond of kinship between them, and whenever they pay a visit to one another, the host provides a special meal for the guest.Even when they are just passing by, it is considered as a bad omen not to visit the homestead of your cousin or to leave it without eating something, no matter how little it may be. This is illustrated by a Gikuyu saying that <b> \"mûihwa ndaimagwo rûnyeni,\"</b> which means, a cousin cannot be denied a meal.]]></string>
    <string name="grandparents"><![CDATA[Grandparents are called <b>gûuka</b> (grandfather) and <b>cûcû</b> (grandmother).The affection between them and the children is very great. Symbolically the children belong to the same age-group as their grandparents, the name given to the first male child is that of his paternal grand-father, and at the time of birth it is announced that it is \" he \" who has come. Similarly the second male child will represent his maternal grandfather. In religious ceremonies the children are treated in the same manner as their grand-parents. The same thing applies to a female child.\\n A boy is called by his grandmother\"<b>mûthuuri wakwa</b>(my husband),\" and a girl is called ”mûiru wakwa(my co-wife).\"The grandfather calls the boy <b>wakinî</b>,\"my equal,\" and the girl <b>mûhiki wakwa</b>, \"my bride.\"This form of address is, of course, used figuratively and as a sign of endearment.]]></string>
    <string name="mothers_sister"><![CDATA[The mother\'s sister is called <b>tata</b>, the same as the father\'s sister, but the relation between her and the children of her sister is entirely different. She is looked upon by the children in the same way as their real mother. The affection and indulgence that she gives to the children and the sympathetic attitude towards them is even greater than that the children can expect from their own mother. Children like to visit or to be visited by their aunt, and whenever such a visit is made it is always an occasion of rejoicing and feasting.\\n The children of both sisters address one another as <b>mûra or mwarî wa tata</b> (son or daughter of my or our aunt), the behaviour pattern between them is almost like brothers and sisters.]]></string>
    <string name="mothers_brother"><![CDATA[The mother\'s brother, who is called <b>mama</b> (my or our uncle), is the only one in the family group who enjoys that title. \'For there is no uncle on the father\'s side. Because those who might be called uncle, according to European system of kinship, are called \"fathers\"in the Gikuyu society. The uncle\'s relation with his sister\'s children is that of fatherly love and affection.He has a certain influence over the children. For instance, before children can be allowed to pierce their ears as a sign of approaching the circumcision ceremony, his permission must be obtained.A gift of five sheep or goats (mburi cia ûihwa) is made by the father to the uncle at a time when the permission is required.]]></string>
    <string name="relatives_by_marriage">After a marriage contract is signed between two families all clan members of both sides become united. They regard one another as mûthoni (relative by marriage). The behaviour towards one\'s relative-in-law is bound up with the word mûthoni, which means one who is bashful or polite. Therefore it follows that every mûthoni must treat another with politeness. In the case of a woman the politeness tends to be bashful, especially in the presence of her relatives-in-law,She must not eat in their presence or utter unpleasant words. She must cover her body properly when sitting or passing near them. She must speak in a sweet and polite tone when talking to them, etc.\\n     The same thing applies to a man. He must show politeness to his mother-in-law or any other member of her age-group. He must give up his seat to her, get out of the way while she is passing. He must cover his body properly in her presence and not use any vulgar language while speaking to her or in her hearing. The father-in-law may not enter the house of his daughter-in-law before she becomes a mother,and as a sign of politeness he must give a sheep or goat on entering her house.</string>
    <string name="nyakiambi">mutumia wa mbere,etagwo nyakiambi tondu niwe wambaga mucii</string>
    <string name="nyakiamburi">mutumia wa keeri, etagwo nyakiamburi tondu kuuma na mburi cia kumugura</string>
    <string name="unduire">
        <u>Mawiko ma ugikuyu</u>\n
1.Ngemi cia uciari\n
2.Mathithio\n
3.Mburi ya ngoi\n
4.Gutigithanio na nyondo/mburi ya gutigithio iria\n
5.Guciarwo ringi/gucokia mwana ihu-ini\n
6.Irua\n
7.Kuhikania\n
8.Kurera (kurera mwana to guthinjira)\n
9.Gutheria mucii/horerio\n
10.Kwigaya \n

        \n <b><u>Ngemi cia gikuyu</u></b>\n
1. Uthamaki\n
2. Utonga\n
3. Ugo\n
4. Urathi\n
5. Ucamba(rugagirwo kahii)\n
        \n <b> <u>Nyama cia mburi ni 13</u> </b>\n
1)Ikengeto (makengeto,mbaru) - mabru ikumi cia miena yothe iri(urio na umutho)\n
2)Honge igiri - Rũhonge(iriyaguo ni atumia)- nyama iria itigaguo waruta maguru na rucuthi\n
3)Rũcuthĩ(muthuri mwene mucii) - nyama ya mugongo,kuuma haria makengeto matinirio\n
4)Guoko - maguru ma mbere meri- kwa urio na kwa umotho\n
5)Kũgũrũ - maguru ma thutha - kwa urio na kwa umotho\n
6)Mũkua- tũhũ - nyama ya mugongo (mbaru cia 8-10 haria makengeto marutiruo)\n
7)Gĩthũũri\n
8)Kĩĩga/Ciĩga(mbaru,ihii) - mbaru cia mbere ithathu iria itigarire waruta makengeto hamwe na nyama ya mugongo, kiiga giatinanio kiumaga nyama igiri\n
9)Ngingo(anake)- nyama ya ngingo\n
Ngaĩ - ya urio na ya umotho, ciriaguo ni athinji\n
Mũtwe(thiya,rurimi na matu(airitu))\n
Mathagiro(4)\n
        \n<b><u>Nyama cia thiini</u></b>\n
Ihu ria mai,muromo wa ihu(ihu ria muthuri), ngirima(ihu ria atumia),mutura wa kibororo(ihii),ngoro,mahuri na ngingo,
        mutura wa kagiri/mbimbi/athuri,wei,mara(mwena muceke ni wa atumia ucio ungi ni wa muthuri), ini, higo, gakuo kaingi/karaguuma.\n
 Rũambũ - maguta ma nda\n
        \nParts which were thrown away\n
Maitho\n
Thũngĩ\n
Mũthĩgi\n
Nyongo\n
    </string>
    <string name="mitugo">Mitugo Ya Gikuyu</string>

</resources>
